<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gallantry unmask'd, or, Women in their proper colours a novel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G176A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08963270</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08963270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41950)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1285:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gallantry unmask'd, or, Women in their proper colours a novel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>155 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B.R. and are to be sold by R. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The history of the Mareschalless de la ferté": p. 81-155.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:42116:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42116:1"/>
                  <p>Gallantry Unmask'd; OR, WOMEN IN Their proper Colours. A NOVEL.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. R.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old Bailey.</hi> 1690.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="novel">
                  <pb facs="tcp:42116:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42116:2"/>
                  <head>GALLANTRY UNMASK'D; OR, <hi>WOMEN</hi> in their Proper Colours.</head>
                  <p>THOSE Women who were naturally inclin'd to Gallantry, were the more encourag'd to it, during the reign of the Great <hi>Alexander,</hi> by that ſplendour they ſaw thoſe Ladies arrive at who had the good fortune to pleaſe him: ſo that there were none but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to charm him; and it being
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42116:3"/> impoſſible for him to ſatisfie all, how bountiful ſoever Nature had been, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eſcap'd him, not ſo much for want of deſire, as ability.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe who were not of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Elect, did not fall under the deſpair, eſpecially thoſe who were ſo generous to expect principally the pleaſures of enjoyment, and had hopes of being acceptable elſewhere. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, their Ambition excepted, which they could not ſatisfie, they might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps find a better account in another place, and to examin the matter critical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a King might perhaps deſerve leſs E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for that, than a Man of a lower Quality: that beſides they might have the pleaſure to change when the Party was no longer agreeable, which good breeding would not have allow'd, had it been their deſtinies to be belov'd by that Great Monarch.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt theſe, none were ſooner comforted than the Mareſchalleſs <hi>de la Ferte,</hi> and Madam <hi>de Lionne:</hi> they had both Age enough to renounce the Vanities of the World; but as there are ſome whom Sin never abandons, ſince they had rais'd their thoughts ſo high, being reſolv'd to convince
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42116:3"/> the World they were ſtill to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu'd, they appear'd in all the gayety of Youth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>De Fieſque</hi> had long been Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi>'s belov'd Gallant, and ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd the pleaſures he gave her by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting his wants; ſo that by her means he made a figure like the reſt of the World. He was not angry at her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pleaſe the King, neither would it have troubled him more had ſhe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in it: but finding, that not conſidering he had ſerv'd her from her youth, ſhe was purveying for her ſelf elſe where, he frankly bid her think well of what ſhe was going to do; that it was enough to be contented with the leavings of a fulſome Husband, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuffering the refuſe of others; that if he had afforded his aſſiſtance to her amour with the King, 'twas upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that he ſhould only partake the pleaſures of the Body, without any intereſt in her affection; but her dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceedings ſufficiently convinc'd him ſhe was in ſearch of ſome new Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouſt; that he was not at all pleas'd at it, and in a word, if ſhe did not reform her Conduct, ſhe might expect from him all the reſentment that an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42116:4"/> injur'd Lover is capable of ſhewing on the like occaſion.</p>
                  <p>The Lady was not at all pleas'd with theſe reproaches, and concluding he would nevertheleſs be happy enough in rendring her his ſervice, being ſo well paid for his pains. You are very pleaſant, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> to talk thus, this is all a Husband can pretend to: But ſhe very well perceiv'd the reaſon of this boldneſs; and it was the favours ſhe had done him, made him preſume ſhe had not the power to leave him: But ſhe would ſoon convince him of the contrary, and ſhe would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately go about it. <hi>De Fieſque</hi> ſmil'd at theſe threats, and the acquaintance he had ſo long with her, perſwading him he lov'd her now no more than a Husband does his Wife, he imagin'd, his Intereſt excepted, it would not be very difficult to forget the loſs. But he found a ſurpriſing return of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for he was no ſooner out of her Lodgings, but he wiſh'd himſelf there again; and had not his pride retain'd him, he would have flown that minute to have ask'd her pardon; yet he could not forbear writing to her to this effect.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42116:4"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <head>Mr. <hi>de Fieſque</hi> to Madam <hi>de Lionne.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>COuld I have endur'd your proceedings without Jealouſie, it would have been an argument that I had but little paſſion for you; but there is a time for all things, and it would afford you too much reaſon of offence to be angry any longer. I muſt confeſs, I cannot forbear loving you, be your Conduct what it will; but yet reflect, if I pardon you ſo eaſily, it is becauſe I am ſo vain to flatter my ſelf I might perhaps be miſtaken; but know likewiſe, you ſhould not have found me ſo good natur'd, had there been any ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect produc'd from your intentions.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Whether Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> took any new offence at the Letter, or had too good an appetite (as is more likely) to be contented with the Count, who who had the reputation of being more Gentile than Vigorous, ſhe threw the Letter into the fire, and told the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, ſhe had no anſwer to return to it. This encreas'd the paſſion of the Lover, who with all haſte imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble flew to her Appartment, telling her, if ſhe would not pardon him, he came
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42116:5"/> to die at her feet, but hop'd his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was not beyond the reach of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that his Notary's Wife, call'd <hi>le Vaſſeur,</hi> had forgiv'n her Husband, tho' he had caus'd her to be proclaim'd a publick Whore by arreſt of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and had long conſin'd her in the <hi>Magdelonnettes</hi> or <hi>Bridewel;</hi> that his Crime was not ſo notorious as the Husband's, who whatever he perceiv'd, was oblig'd by the Articles and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of Marriage to be ſilent; that there was no ſuch Law for the Lovers, but on the contrary, Complaints were always permitted, as the kind effects of Paſſion, and to deny him, was an infringement on his undoubted Right.</p>
                  <p>Tho' the only difference between Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> and Mademoiſelle <hi>le Vaſſeur</hi> was, that one was a Notary's, and the other the Wife to a Miniſter of State; that one was declar'd ſo by an Arreſt of Parliament, and the other by the Voice of the People, which is nevertheleſs the Voice of God; the Compariſon did not pleaſe her, and ſhe told <hi>Fieſque,</hi> he was very impudent in making the parallel. <hi>De Fieſque</hi> knew enough to anſwer about her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but coming to her with a deſign
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42116:5"/> of re-accommodation, to which perhaps his interſt had inclin'd him, he continu'd in the ſame tune he began, tho' to little purpoſe; for Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who would not be inſulted over, and being bankrupt in Virtue, took not ſuch care of the appearances of it, told him, with a deſign to enrage him the more, that ſhe would make a Lover to his face; and that the more he ſhould be concern'd at it, the more pleaſure it would afford her. <hi>De Fieſque</hi> was ſo incens'd at this harſh reply, that tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Lute that was in her Chamber, and with which he us'd ſometimes to divert her, he broke it in a thouſand pieces. He told her, that ſince ſhe took ſuch pains to torment his Heart, he would revenge himſelf upon that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument which had heretofore given her ſuch pleaſure; and that as ſhe might perhaps make choice of one that could touch it as well as himſelf, he ſhould be glad to prevent that from ſerving another which had been of uſe to him: But he had ſcarcely ſpoke, when ſhe made anſwer, whom ſhe choſe ſhould have no occaſion to animate himſelf with Preludes; that ſhe had often indeed counterfeited a delight
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42116:6"/> to hear him play, knowing nothing could otherwiſe be expected from him; but ſhe was of the ſame opinion as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he had done well in breaking the Lute, ſince it only ſerv'd to put her in mind of his weakneſs, and when that object was away there was nothing to recal ſo diſagreeable an Idea, and he had by it done no more than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented her deſign.</p>
                  <p>As one Reproach draws on another, this Converſation, how diſagreeable ſoever, would not have ended ſo ſoon, had not the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> made a viſit. He ſoon perceiv'd the condition of the poor Lute, and irnagin'd a quarrel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, which he was quickly cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of when he had look'd upon the two Lovers. He took a great freedom in his Speech, and delighted in Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery. Madam, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> I find there will ſometimes be fallings out, and one of you has reveng'd himſelf upon that innocent Lute; if it was you, Madam, perhaps you had reaſon for it, and I cannot blame you; but if it was my Friend, he was very much in the wrong, for he has not liv'd to this Age with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing that Women are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be amus'd with ſo fooliſh a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42116:6"/> toy, and it gives us time to prepare to render 'em better ſervice.</p>
                  <p>This Diſcourſe had been ſufficient to have offended, not only a nice Lady, but one that would have appear'd ſo; yet Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who lik'd the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> thought only of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him that ſhe was breaking off for ever with <hi>Fieſque,</hi> that if his heart had thought any thing in favour of her, no time might be loſt; and not reſlecting that ſhe was going to diſhonour her ſelf, and that on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, a Lover had rather doubt of his Miſtreſs's intriegue than be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of it, eſpecially by her ſelf. What would you have, Sir, <hi>ſays ſhe,</hi> Engagements cannot laſt for ever, and I cannot deny but I have had ſome conſideration for the Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> yet it is hard enough that we are bound for ever to our Husbands, without running the ſame ſate with our Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants; this would make us more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy than we are: we chuſe a Lover to ſerve us whilſt he is agrecable, and 'twould be horrid were we oblig'd to keep him when he diſpleaſes us. Add, Madam, if you pleaſe, <hi>ſays the Duke,</hi> when he can render you no further ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42116:7"/>
'tis for this you chuſe 'em, and what tyranny would it be to give the World occaſion to talk, and not reap the profit of it, for which alone you Women can conſent to ſacrifice your Reputations? For my part, continued he, I ſhould approve that, according to the cuſtom amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglios were erected, not truly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe, as they do, the invalid Women, ſince they will permit me, I hope, to believe with all reſpect to 'em, that at any age they will ſtill have more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite than my ſelf, whom neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I have no little opinion of: but for poor, decayed Lovers, who are ſo worn out in their Miſtreſs's embraces, that they are incapable of rendring 'em any further ſervice, if this ſhould happen, and I had any part of the Government, I do aſſure you, I would firſt of all give my Vote for an Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there for our Friend: What ſay you, Madam, would not this do well? And think you not that there are perſons in as good health put every day into the Hoſpital of the Invalids? How ſtrangely you talk? <hi>cry'd Madam</hi> de Lionne, and if we did not know that you have no ill meaning in what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42116:7"/> you ſay, who would not bluſh at your diſcourſe. With this ſhe put her Fan before her face, to make him believe ſhe was yet capable of ſome confuſion; but the Duke, who knew how long ſhe had parted with her Modeſty, ſmil'd to himſelf at her deportment, not caring to drive the Intriegue far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>The Count had heard all this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out joyning in the Converſation, and he found that a laſting Intriegue was not unlike a Marriage, the tenderneſs whereof is ſcarcely to be perceiv'd, till the bonds are breaking; he rav'd, he ſigh'd, and the preſence of the Duke was not able to make him reſtrain himſelf; they were good friends, and Confidents to each other a thouſand times; and two days were not paſs'd, ſince the Duke deſired him to do him what ſervice he could with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs <hi>de Coeuvres,</hi> Madam <hi>de Lionne's</hi> Daughter: For this reaſon <hi>Fieſque</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to be gone, hoping the Duke would be more ſerious in his abſence; but he, who ſeldom had this Character with the Women, careleſs of his Friend's Intereſt, reſolv'd to ſee how far Madam <hi>de Lionne's</hi> folly would
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42116:8"/> carry her. No ſooner then was the Count gone, but ſhe ſaid a thouſand things to diſcover her paſſion, not in formal terms, but in words intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough to one of a wit inferiour to the Duke's. And if the Duke had not fear'd that the complying with her might have been an obſtacle to his amour with the Marchioneſs <hi>de Coeuvres,</hi> neither his cruelty nor ſcrupulouſneſs would have ſuffer'd her to langniſh any longer; but doubting leſt the young Marchioneſs, whoſe Soul was not ſo hardned as her Mothers, might make a difficulty to hear him, pretended to underſtand nothing; and choſe rather to paſs for a dull Brute, than occaſion a difference with his Miſtreſs.</p>
                  <p>He found, when he went away, the Count <hi>de Fieſque</hi> waiting for him at the corner of a Street, who ask'd him if he had done any thing for him? No, my poor Count, <hi>anſwered he,</hi> for I did not take you to be Fool enough to be ſo concern'd for an old Whore; but ſince I know your weakneſs, let me tell you in two words, that if you do not ſerve me with the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>de Coeuvres,</hi> I will do you ſuch diſ-ſervice with her Mother, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42116:8"/> there will be no returning for you Do you hear, amongſt our ſelves, I believe that the brawny Calves of my Legs, and my broad Shoulders begin to pleaſe her more than your eaſie Air, and <hi>Barbary</hi> ſhape: and if ſhe once have the tryal of it, I leave you to judge what will become of you. The Count deſir'd him to be ſerious: The Duke told him, he might take it as he pleas'd, but he told him nothing but the truth; and the other being oblig'd to believe him, after he had ſworn ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times to it, he deſir'd him not to hunt in his purlues, confeſſing inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly, that he lov'd her for ſeveral reaſons, that is, for giving him both Money and Pleaſure. This confeſſion of the Count's to any other, would have rather excited than abated their deſires; all the Youth at the Court making it their buſineſs to be too hard for the Ladies; but the Duke, who was the moſt generous of all Men, bid him reſt ſatisfi'd upon that point, and that both Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> and her Money ſhould be ſafe for him; and that (excepting the pleaſure of Cuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olding a Miniſter of State) what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence ſoever was given for it,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42116:9"/> would be leſs than he deſerv'd; that nevertheleſs he ſhould not remain ſo aſſur'd upon this promiſe as to neglect the ſervice he expected from him, and that ſometimes that was done out of Revenge which was not performed for Love; and that if he did not aſſiſt him with the Marchioneſs, he would place himſelf ſo well with the Mother, that it ſhould be very difficult for him, as he ſaid before, to become her Patroon again.</p>
                  <p>Altho' this was ſpoke in Raillery, it nevertheleſs made a violent impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the Count <hi>de Fieſque</hi>'s thoughts; but as it was impoſlible for him to live without knowing whether his Miſtreſs was unfaithful, he writ her theſe words as from the Duke; and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was oblig'd to borrow another hand, his own being ſo well known to Madam <hi>de Lionne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <hi>YOu muſt needs have an ill opinion of me for giving ſuch reception to all the favours you gave me; but, Madam, when it is ones ill fortune to be in the Chirurgeon's hands, is it not better to ſeem not to underſtand, than expoſe a Lady to ſuch certain repentance as muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42116:9"/> reaſonably occaſion hatred to ſucceed the friendſhip? If they tell me true, I ſhall be well in eight days; it will ſeem a long time to one that has more than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment at his heart; but give me leave to break off this entertainment, it excites ſome motions that are not proper for me till a perfect cure; I hope it will be ſpeedy; and remember, that I am more to be pitied than you imagine, ſince that which is a ſign of health in others, is a token of illneſs in me, or at leaſt an aggravation of it.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>It is hard to ſay whether Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> had more Grief or Joy at the receipt of this Letter; for, as ſhe was glad at the hopes that were given her, ſo on the other part, ſhe was griev'd at the accident that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd her to wait; ſo that divided between both extreams, ſhe remain'd ſome time in doubt whether ſhe ſhould return an anſwer; but the Meſſenger preſſing her to come to a determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, her Temper carried it, and thinking that ſhe had in earneſt an affair with the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> ſhe call'd for Ink and Paper, and writ theſe words,</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42116:10"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <head>A Letter from Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> to the Duke <hi>de Saux.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>IT is not a moment ſince I believ'd it the greateſt unhappineſs to have to do with a Brute; but now, methinks it is far worſe to have an affair with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchee; if you had been only inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I might have hop'd, in ſpeaking yet plainer to you than I have done, to make you at laſt underſtand my Language; but what does your underſtanding it now ſignifie, ſince you cannot return an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer? This accident has thrown me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a deſpair; for who can ever aſſure me that I can place a confidence in you; there are ſo many Quacks at</hi> Paris, <hi>and if by misfortune, you are fallen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any of their hands, into what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity will you reduce thoſe who ſhall fall into yours? if decency would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to ſend you my Chirurgeon, he is an able Man, and would ſoon lead you out of this misfortune; let me know your thoughts of it; for ſince I can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready forgive ſuch a crime as yours, I am too ſenſible I can never defend my ſelf againſt any thing you deſire.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42116:10"/>
                  <p>Oh, the fooliſh, ſilly, lewd Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, cry'd the Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> when he had read the Letter, and muſt not I have an heart as vile as hers, if I can love her after this: and imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe to be his true thoughts, he put the Letter in his pocket, and went to her with a compos'd Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and forc'd Air. As I have been your Friend a long time, Madam, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> it is impoſſible for me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce your Intereſt for any ſmall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and as a confirmation of what I ſay, I recommend to you one that belongs to me, who is incomparable for ſome things; I mean my Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon: you ought not to refuſe him, for no doubt but you will ſoon have occaſion for him, if you follow the courſes you take. Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> was in confuſion at this diſcourſe; ſhe was in fear of ſome diſcovery; but the Count ſoon confirm'd her; for his face grown red with anger, and not keeping the calmneſs of temper he intended, Oh, ye infamous Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>continued he,</hi> are theſe the proofs you give me of your friendſhip, ſnew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her the Letter, what Woman is there, tho' never ſuch a Proſtitute,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42116:11"/> who would write in theſe terms: Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi> ſhall know it, 'tis a revenge I owe my ſelf; he ſhall do me reaſon, ſince I have not the power to do it my ſelf, and if he has the baſeneſs to forgive it, I'le take the pleaſure to tell it every one, and let all <hi>Paris</hi> know what you are.</p>
                  <p>He made other reproaches which were all endured by this Woman, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary patience; for finding her ſelf in his power, ſhe durſt not incenſe him more. She had recourſe to tears, but he appear'd unalter'd, departing in great fury. Her Tears which were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly artificial, were ſoon dryed up when he was gone, ſo ſhe ſent immediately for the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> deſiring him to draw her out of this affair; and ſince it had happen'd to her by uſing his name, he was ingag'd in it further than he imagin'd; and to oblige him not to refuſe her his aſſiſtance, ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd him he ſhould be ſure of hers towards her Daughter, and kept her word like a Woman of honour, for when the Duke had acquainted her how the Intrigue ſtood, ſhe fully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon her inclinations, which were already very much in favour of the Duke.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42116:11"/>
                  <p>But yet ſhe articled with him, that this Intrigue ſhould not be at all to the prejudice of her Rights, and to confirm the Treaty, ſhe demanded ſome earneſt of his promiſes. The Duke had paſs'd the night with <hi>Louiſon d'Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quien,</hi> a famous Curteſan, and was not in a condition to afford her any; yet thinking that a man of his age could not long be out of ſtock, he asked her if ſhe would have money in hand, or defer the payment to the following night. Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who knew Man to be mortal, thought ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney beſt, but nevertheleſs ſhe told him, if he was not provided with the whole Sum, ſhe would give him credit for the remainder for the time he ſhould require.</p>
                  <p>The Duke quickly underſtood the meaning of this, and placed the Cuſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for a Table whereon to Count the money; but when he pull'd forth his purſe, it was quite empty, to the great aſtoniſhment of the one, and no leſs Confuſion of the other. She flew from his arms in an anger more eaſie to be imagin'd, than diſcrib'd, and as he would have held her, giving her lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing kiſſes: What would you have,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42116:12"/> Sir, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> would you give me great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er tokens of your impotency! I would dye, Madam, <hi>anſwered the Duke,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair my honour, and one of 'em muſt happen to me this moment. Is it of a violent death Sir, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> that you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to dye? rallying him, if ſo, you muſt make uſe of a rope, for who can believe your Sword proper for that purpoſe, and when you could not find one drop of blood, having ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for it, it is more reaſonable to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the Source will be leſs in an Action ſo contrary to nature. When ſhe had ſaid this, ſhe plac'd her ſelf upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chair, and to hide her anger, took up a Skreen that lay by chance near her; fortune would have it, that upon it was painted the ſtory of the Marqueſs <hi>de Langes,</hi> who was divorc'd for his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency. The Tryal by the Parliament was deſcrib'd likewiſe, and Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> caſting her Eyes upon it, here, <hi>ſays ſhe,</hi> you are drawn to the Life, it is impoſſible to do it better; and if you remember what you told us of your abilities the other day, you will find, that except the demanding a Tryal, you have both performed alike. You have only now to marry, 'tis the way
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42116:12"/> to ſpread your Reputation. And I do not doubt but to have you as well as that able man, for an Ornament to my Chimney. You have reaſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult over me, Madam, <hi>anſwered the Duke,</hi> and my offence is of a nature never to be pardon'd; for my part I know not my ſelf, and after I have conſidered my misfortune, I can only attribute it to one thing. You have heard, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he,</hi> of the Perfume call'd <hi>Pulvillio,</hi> a Curſe upon <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>A famous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender of a Bath, now firſt</hi> Valet de Chambre <hi>to the King.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Vienne</hi> for helping me to this Invention, which to give me a good ſcent, has made me inſenſible. But Madam, the Charm will only laſt till I have bath'd, give me ſufficient time for that I conjure you, and I oblige my ſelf to pay you Intereſt for my preſent defailure. Nevertheleſs remember, Madam, that I am not the only Man <hi>Vienne</hi> has ingag'd in theſe unfortunate accidents, the ſame thing happen'd to the Count de St. <hi>Poll</hi> the other day, when he wanted his Compliment to a fine young Lady; I made a jeſt of it then, but ſince, to my great regret, I have made tryal of it my ſelf, it would be Hereſie not to believe it. Theſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42116:13"/> words afforded ſome conſolation to Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> ſhe had heard of the Count <hi>de</hi> St. <hi>Poll's</hi> Adventure, ſo that asking the particulars from the Duke, he gave her what information he could, and to make a greater impreſſion of the truth of it, he repeated a Song made upon that occaſion to an air in <hi>Pſyche.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She ſuffered him to ſing one verſe without interruption, becauſe ſhe had a mind to know the whole Effect of this damn'd powder, which ſhe thought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd much more to be condemn'd to the fire, than the works of <hi>Petit</hi> ſentenced to the Flames by Judgment of Parliament. But as he was going to purſue with the other Verſe, hold Duke, <hi>cry'd ſhe,</hi> tho' you have one qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Muſitian, you want the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and are in the number of thoſe that one would give one Piſtol to ſing, and ten to leave off. The Duke told her he had nothing to ſay againſt her Reproaches, and ſhe us'd him too fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably, conſidering his fault. But whilſt he thus humbled himſelf, he found a willingneſs in a certain part to frame a better Excuſe, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Eſtabliſh his Reputation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42116:13"/> a Bath, he made ſome approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, which gave him hopes of a happy ſucceſs. Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> was much ſurpriſed, and greatly overjoy'd at the ſame time at this ſudden alteration: but yet miſtruſting her good Fortune, ſhe yielded her hand to be better aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, and it being difficult to deceive her on that ſcore, ſhe ſoon perceiv'd 'twas to little purpoſe to flatter her ſelf with better fortune. The Duke was of the ſame opinion, when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that weeping which he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a more manly figure, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting in a vexation not to be equall'd, he could ſcarcely forbear to give ſad tokens of his deſpair. Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> would not let him begon without a new raillery; do not think, <hi>ſays ſhe,</hi> that this accident ſhall be in the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the friendſhip I have for you, you ſhall perceive it by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of my Daughter, for inſtead of acquainting her of your inclinations for her, I will contrive that you ſhall never ſee her; this will be the means to preſerve your Reputation, and the good Opinion ſhe has of you: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>continued ſhe,</hi> that this is the beſt ſervice I can render you, in the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42116:14"/> you are in, and you will owe me no little Obligation for it.</p>
                  <p>The Duke thought it not convenient to give her any anſwer, but going in all haſte to <hi>Vienne's;</hi> you and your curſed <hi>Pulvillio</hi> have ruined my Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>cry'd he,</hi> and I'le burn your Houſe immediately, if you promiſe me not to throw away what you have left of it. <hi>Vienne</hi> found him very angry, but knew not the meaning of it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Duke had told him his misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, concealing the name of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Upon my Faith, <hi>ſays Vienne,</hi> this is a pleaſant ſtory of you, and your <hi>Pulvillio;</hi> remain here with me but two or three days from the Company of <hi>Loüiſon d'Arquien,</hi> the Count <hi>de Tallard,</hi> or any of that kind, and you will find if it be my <hi>Pulvillio</hi> that hinders you from doing your Duty. This was a Banter, cunningly enough invented by the Count <hi>de</hi> St. <hi>Poll</hi> to excuſe himſelf to <hi>La Mignard,</hi> whom he had long courted to a meeting but when he had promiſed the poor Girl Mountains and Miracles, could never arrive to the third part of my proweſs, who am above twice his age. I cannot blame him for making the beſt Excuſe he could for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42116:14"/> himſelf, but I ſhould have been oblig'd to him, not to have done it at my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence. I have ten thouſand Crowns worth of <hi>Pulvillio</hi> by me, and do you but as well as he, ſpread your mad fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies about the Town, and I ſhall be ſent to Goal.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vienne</hi> took the freedom of telling all the Gentlemen of their little faults, ſo that the Count was not angry to hear of his, but on the contrary, told him, he would try who had moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to that intent, would not leave his Houſe for four or five days, and he ſhould ſee he would refrain from the Company of the Count <hi>de Tallard,</hi> and <hi>Loüiſon,</hi> if he would but take care to fetch a piece of Champain Wine, that his Servants had diſcover'd to be excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, from St. <hi>John's</hi> Church Yard, at the Sign of the two <hi>Torches;</hi> and that they might not drink it alone, he ſhould acquaint the Marqueſs <hi>de Sable,</hi> and two or three of his Friends, with his deſign to treat 'em with a diſh of meat at his Houſe; and that they might bring Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>du Meſnil</hi> with 'em, were they dexterous enough to perſwade her from the arms of her old <hi>Mareſchal,</hi> that brags he has a part of his Body as ſtiff as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42116:15"/> his Wooden Leg. That he did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this Woman for any lew'd deſign, ſince no body but the Marqueſs <hi>de Sable</hi> would be contented with the Mareſchal <hi>de Grancey</hi>'s leavings; and that he, for his part, had rather lye with a Woman moderately handſom, who had an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging Gallant, than with the moſt Charming Woman in the World, that did, like her, proſtitute her ſelf to ſo naſty a Fellow as the <hi>Mareſchal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vienne</hi> told him 'twas well he was ſo nice, and that he daily ſhewed it ſufficiently by his intimacy with <hi>Loüi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> the refuſe of the Nation. That as it was not his buſineſs, he had nothing to ſay to it, but as for Madam <hi>du Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nil,</hi> he did not truly deſire her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to bring a Scandal upon his Houſe; that they might eat and drink as much as they pleas'd, but he had no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accommodation for 'em.</p>
                  <p>After this, he went as the Duke commanded him, and the Gueſts brought <hi>du Meſnil</hi> with 'em, and made ſuch good Entertainment, that the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> ſoon perceiv'd the Witchcraft of the <hi>Pulvillio</hi> would not laſt long. About the end of the Feaſt, a Servant acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Company, there was one to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42116:15"/> for the Marqueſs <hi>de Sable,</hi> they bid him be call'd in, and were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſurpris'd to find him a Guard belonging to a Mareſchal of <hi>France.</hi> He told the Marqueſs he had orders to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him in <hi>Biſhops-fort,</hi> which ſtartled the Company, that knew not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. The Marqueſs only laught at it, and as they were going to ask him the meaning; Go, go, return (<hi>ſays he to the Guard</hi>) to the old Fool the <hi>Mareſchal,</hi> tell him we are drinking his health, and that afterwards we will kiſs his Miſtreſs, and if he has a mind to his ſhare, let him come to us; give him a glaſs of Wine, <hi>ſays he to a Lacquy,</hi> this is all he will get by his Journey. Every one knew by what the Marqueſs ſpoke, that the Complement came from the Mareſchal <hi>de Grancey,</hi> and before the Guard had drunk his Glaſs, ſo many Ralleys had paſs'd at it, that, tho' he was a notable drinker, he was forc'd to break off in the middle of his draught, to deſire the Company to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſaying any thing diſreſpectfully concerning he Mareſchal; at this every body was ready to laugh out, and the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> who was neareſt the Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, got up with a pretence to make
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42116:16"/> him drink the remainder of his Wine, but ſpilt it all maliciouſly upon his Clothes, and Linnen. The <hi>Guard</hi> was almoſt angry, but the Marqueſs appeas'd him by preſenting another brimmer to him, deſiring him to drink it to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal's health. After this they gave him another, and in a little time he was ſo drunk, that no body rail'd at the Mareſchal more than himſelf. In this good humour they ſent him back, and the Mareſchal, impatient to know the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his Deputy, had conducted him within a hundred paces of the Gate, he no ſooner ſaw him, but he threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of his Coach to ask him what was the reaſon he ſtaid ſo long? He found the <hi>Guard</hi> was drunk by the firſt word he ſpoke, and growing into a great paſſion, call'd for a Cane, but none being found in the Coach, he bid a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of his, call'd <hi>Gendarme,</hi> (who was both his <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> and Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, tho' he could neither write nor read,) to unbrace his Leg, and that ſhould ſerve him for a ſtick. <hi>Gendarme</hi> told him it could not be; and upon this he ſlew at his Peruque, diſcharging his anger upon him. When the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal was tyred with beating him; he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42116:16"/> call'd the <hi>Guard,</hi> who was ſlunk off, and asking him freſh queſtions, his anger was much more encreaſt, when he heard <hi>du Meſnil</hi> was of the debauchery. For the occaſion of his anger hitherto, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was becauſe ſhe had ſeen the Marqueſs <hi>de Sable</hi> privately, and this was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he would have ſent him to Priſon.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Guard</hi> had no ſooner ſpoke, but he cry'd out he was undone, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hand to <hi>Gendarme,</hi> come <hi>ſays he,</hi> let us forget what's paſs'd, and tell me if I be not very unhappy, what is to be done my Friend? But be ſure you ſay nothing of it to my Wife, for you know ſhe always told me what a Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an this was. <hi>Gendarme</hi> would not for twice as many blows, but this had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd; he laugh'd in his ſleeve, and would make him no anſwer. The <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal</hi> deſir'd him again to forget all injuries, and to put him in good hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, promis'd to give him the ſute he had on that day. <hi>Gendarme</hi> was a little appeas'd at that promiſe, but glad of the opportunity to mortify him, Have not I often told you, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> as well as the <hi>Mareſchaleſs,</hi> that ſhe was a Whore? were I in your place, as ſoon as I came home, I would turn that Baſtard out of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42116:17"/> doors, who is none of yours I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you, and yet you Educate him with the greateſt Faith in the World, whilſt your own Daughters, more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps out of neceſſity than inclination — Ah Traytor, <hi>ſays the Mareſchal, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him,</hi> will you always be reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? What my Boy is not my own; he does not reſemble me<note place="margin">Large flat Ears.</note> like two drops of Water? has he not the Ears of the <hi>Grancey</hi>'s? a ſure ſign he is of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: I'le have you hang'd, and tho' I ſav'd you from the halter at <hi>Thionville,</hi> I'le ſend you to your former deſtiny.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gendarme,</hi> altho' he had known he ſhould be worſe treated than before, could not forbear anſwering theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives. This is ſine, <hi>crys he,</hi> to take a Baſtards part, and neglect your own Daughters, I thought you might be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at what I was ſaying of them, but for ought I ſind that's your leaſt care. 'Tis true, he has your great Ears, but is that ſo unqueſtionable a ſign he is your own, as you believe? How many Women bring forth Children with ſome particular mark, when the Mothers have taken too much notice of ſome diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Object; your Mother perhaps might
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42116:17"/> look upon — he meant an Aſs, but dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to ſpeak the Word, he mutter'd it to himſelf. The <hi>Mareſchal</hi> took but little notice of it, and being appeas'd becauſe he yielded him the reſemblance of the Ears; well then, <hi>ſays he,</hi> what is to be done? ſhall I ſuffer a Girl to remain in theſe Villains hands, whom they have certainly taken away by force. <hi>Gendarme</hi> who knew they were at a debauch, and being dry with rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thinking a Glaſs or two of Wine would fall to his ſhare, could he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the <hi>Mareſchal</hi> to go thither; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſet his Face to Counterfeit a Man of thought; upon my Faith, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> if you will take my advice, we will go immediately to 'em; we ſhall compaſs two ends in it; one the bringing back of <hi>Meſnil,</hi> and the other the hindring the accompliſhing perhaps of ſomething that may not pleaſe you. For how do we know, Wine renders ſome very brisk; and makes 'em per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form marvels on thoſe occaſions: But ſhall not I venture my ſelf too much, quoth the <hi>Mareſchal?</hi> How critical you are, cry's <hi>Gendarme,</hi> when you go every day you know where, do you make a ſcruple of going to <hi>Viennes,</hi> where all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42116:18"/> the people of Quality rendezvous.</p>
                  <p>Theſe reaſons were ſufficient to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Mareſchal, but deſirous to be accompanied with a Guard, he would have had that fellow that had been there before follow him, but he was not to be found; for repoſing himſelf upon a Stall, he was fallen ſo faſt aſleep, that when they found him it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to wake him. The Mareſchal would have had <hi>Gendarme</hi> put on his Coat, but he not caring to be oblig'd to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hazardous complement to thoſe, of whoſe diſcretion and reſpect he was ſo little aſſur'd, told him, he was too well known by the Company to take any figure but his own; and the Mareſchal yielding to his reaſons, ſuffered the Guard to ſleep undiſturb'd.</p>
                  <p>No ſooner was he arriv'd at <hi>Vienne</hi>'s, but he made ſo much haſte into the room where the Company was, that they had not time to acquaint 'em of his coming; they were extremely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee him, but Madam <hi>de Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nil</hi> moſt of all, who thought after this he would no longer furniſh for her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipage. The Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> as the moſt conſiderable, began to ſpeak firſt, telling the Mareſchal, that having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42116:18"/> to be merry, he ſent to invite this company, who going to Madam <hi>du Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nil</hi>'s, would have engag'd her of the party, but ſhe was ſo averſe to it, that they were forc'd to carry her in their arms to the Coach, and they found their Company was not at all pleaſant to her; for ſhe had neither eat nor drunk ſince ſhe was there, and that they would never hereafter force any body againſt their inclinations.</p>
                  <p>The Mareſchal eaſily ſwallow'd this diſcourſe, and deſirous to make <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darme</hi> take notice of it, whom he thought behind him, but who was at the Cupboard drinking of brimmers of Wine; he gave a Lacquey, who was bringing a Ragouſt to make 'em reliſh the Liquor, ſuch a blow on his arm, that the Diſh was thrown down. This broke off the diſcourſe, and he thought himſelf oblig'd to excuſe it: They told him it was no matter, bid him not concern himſelf, for the entertainment was ſo good, that there was enough left for him and them too: At the ſame time, the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> took him by the Arm, making him ſit down between <hi>du Meſnil</hi> and himſelf; and every thing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42116:19"/> was ſo well, that they began to eat and drink as before.</p>
                  <p>Madam <hi>du Meſnil,</hi> who was full up to the very Throat, affected a great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and Melancholy, and 'tis hard to ſay in which ſhe was the greateſt Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite. Every one told her they won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſhe would not eat, now, ſince ſhe had all ſhe deſir'd ſo near her; but ſince the Mareſchal did not preſs her to it, as ſhe expected, ſhe refus'd it in a languiſhing air, which made thoſe ſmile who knew how ſhe behav'd her ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came in. The Mareſchal, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead with hunger, thought of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſilling his belly; and tho' he ſpoke ſome few words to oblige her to the ſame, yet ſhe had a mind to be more entreated. After he had appeas'd his hunger, being now at leiſure to take care of her, grow more gallant. She ſeem'd to yield to what he deſir'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to eat a freſh, tho' her health ran no little danger by it.</p>
                  <p>Hereupon the Company ſaid, 'twas eaſie to perceive who had the power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her: This made the Mareſchal ſmile in his ſleeve, and he was ſo tickled at it, that he could not forbear tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Ladies toes in ſign of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42116:19"/> friendſhip. The Debauch was drove on to exceſs, and when they had rail'd at all the World, they began to ſpeak ill of one another. The Mareſchal told the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> that he need not wonder his being ſo luſty and fat, when his Brother the Marqueſs <hi>de Ragni</hi> was ſo thin and lean; that he was made between two Doors, when his Brother was got in a Bed; that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing joys were greater than thoſe expected in courſe, and he could let him know, if he did not already, that he owed as much reſpect to the Duke <hi>de Roquelaure</hi> as to his own Father. The Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> to return it in his own coyn, told him, that he could not ſpeak ſo preciſely of his, ſince his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had had ſo many Gallants, that it was impoſſible for him to ſay to which he ow'd his Birth; that it was pity his Daughter was not educated by ſo able a Woman; that perhaps they might not have been ſo high and proud; for the only difference of their Temper and their Grandmother's, was, that they have two Princes for their Gallants, when ſhe always took the firſt that came: That nevertheleſs it was reported they held not always
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42116:20"/> their Hearts ſo high; for if Fame was to be credited, they had no great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to one of their Servants, but it was not to be mention'd for fear of injuring them, and he was ready to ſign, if he pleas'd, that it was only a ſtory invented by ſome malicious body.</p>
                  <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de Grancey</hi> ſwore it was an untruth; that it was true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, there was one of the Servants more agreeable to 'em than the reſt, for his Perſon, Dreſſing, and Wit; but ſeeing the Town talk'd of it, he had turn'd him away, to cut off all colour to theſe falſe reports; and to prove what he ſaid to be authentick, he call'd for ſome Wine, proteſting that he would drink four Glaſſes in each hand, and that they ſhould hear him after that ſwear the ſame thing, and what could be a greater proof of the truth of it, ſince in <hi>Vino Veritas,</hi> the honeſt Drunkard always ſpeaks his mind. This was too plain to be deny'd; and they fell into diſcourſe of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of <hi>Monſieur</hi> with Mademoiſelle <hi>de Grancey,</hi> and upon the paſſion of Monſieur the Duke for her Siſter the Counteſs <hi>de Maré,</hi> which gave an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42116:20"/> to one of the Company to ſing ſome Verſes made upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
                  <p>The Mareſchal was ſo far in his Cups, that he would by all means learn the Song, and ſing it with the reſt; this diverted 'em for ſome time, after which they began to think of retiring home. The Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> forgetting his promiſe to <hi>Vienne,</hi> went into his Coach, with a reſolution to paſs the night with <hi>du Meſnil,</hi> if the Mareſchal <hi>de Grancey,</hi> who had taken her into his, ſhould ſet her down at her Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. To this purpoſe he commanded a Footman to dog her, and to bring him an anſwer at a place appointed. The Boy ſoon return'd, and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that the Mareſchal, after he had ſet her down, was gone home, he drove to her Lodgings, where he paſs'd the night. Much Wine had paſs'd, and not caring much to force himſelf, he knew not whether the charm of the Pulvillio was broke, but put all off till the Morrow; and he was faſt aſleep when <hi>Gendarme</hi> was knocking at the door; <hi>du Meſnil,</hi> not daring to refuſe him entrance, ſince he came from the Patroon, had ſcarce time to wake the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42116:21"/> Duke, and deſire him to ſlip behind a Curtain. <hi>Gendarme,</hi> who was very diligent to take notice of any thing that might diſquiet his Maſter, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, as he was making the comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that there were two priuts tumbled in the Bed; and impatient to tell it the old Fellow, he ran at an unuſual rate, and came to <hi>de Grancey</hi> quite out of breath.</p>
                  <p>The Mareſchal enquir'd the occaſion of his haſte; to tell you, anſwer'd he, that you are the greateſt Bubble in the World; and whilſt you ſleep ſo peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably here, there are ſine things doing for you abroad; that all the Children which you fancy your own, have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Father, for all their fine Ears per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps; and that in a word, you are a Cuckold, an egregious doating Cuckold. Do but riſe, continued he, and you may ſtill find the Hare in the form, or elſe the print of his ſteps ſo plain, that it will not be difficult to trace him. The Mareſchal, who knew what pleaſure he took to raiſe his doubts, bid him take care of what he ſaid, that his life was in danger, for he would never more forgive him: but nevertheleſs he call'd for his Leg and his Cloaths, and was in ſuch haſte
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42116:21"/> to be dreſs'd, and <hi>Gendarme</hi> ſo concern'd to make good his promiſe, that betwixt 'em his Truſs was forgot.</p>
                  <p>The ſhaking of the Coach ſoon made the <hi>Mareſchal</hi> perceive what he wanted, they muſt needs go back to fetch it, and in this time, the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> was dreſs'd and gone. <hi>Du Meſnil</hi> knew how little kindneſs <hi>Gendarme</hi> had for her, and therefore caus'd the Bed to be new made, and afterwards went fairly into the middle of it. It was a farce to ſee the Truſs put on in the Coach; <hi>Gendarme</hi> ſwore he forgot it on purpoſe to let the Bird eſcape; and the Mareſchal ſaid, <hi>Gendarme</hi> did it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for an excuſe: And in fine, it was very diverting to hear their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, which made ſuch a noiſe that drew the Rabble about the Coach: the Footmen, accuſtom'd to theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, diſpers'd the lookers-on, and the <hi>Mareſchal</hi> drew the Curtains to hide his Infirmity from thoſe that knew it not.</p>
                  <p>The Affair being accompliſh'd with much pains, they continued their way, and arriving at <hi>du Meſnil</hi>'s, <hi>Gendarme</hi> was extremely aſtoniſh'd to find but one print in the Bed when he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42116:22"/> two. The <hi>Mareſchal</hi> perceiv'd his ſurpriſe, and fearing leſt he ſhould get firſt to the door, run in all haſte to prevent it, but his wooden Leg ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, he fell and hurt himſelf. <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darme</hi> finding that tho' he was in the right, he muſt bear all the blame, took that opportunity to eſcape, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the <hi>Mareſchal;</hi> he ſwore he would have him hang'd and damn'd; and this encourag'd <hi>du Meſnil,</hi> who was in fear leſt he ſhould give more credit to him than her ſelf.</p>
                  <p>She gave him her hand to help him up, and when he had recover'd his breath, he freely confeſs'd what had paſs'd, begging her pardon for his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſuſpicions. When ſhe found it went ſo well, ſhe thought it proper to give him many harſh reprimands, demanding if this was a recompence for what ſhe did every day for his ſake, forgetting nothing that might confirm her innocence, and bring him to a thorow Repentance. He gave all the ſigns of it that were to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin'd, but nothing pleas'd her ſo much as a Note he ſent to a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Prieſt, deſiring him to return
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42116:22"/> thanks for the diſcovery he had made of <hi>Gendarme</hi>'s wickedneſs.</p>
                  <p>Whilſt the <hi>Mareſchal</hi> was thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted at his good fortune in his good Miſtreſs, the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> thought of re-eſtabliſhing his Reputation with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Lionne;</hi> and what aſſurance ſoever he might have in his Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, he nevertheleſs not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain'd from ſeeing the Count <hi>de Tallard</hi> and <hi>Louiſon,</hi> but dieted of what he thought would contribute to a vigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous health; and thinking himſelf then in a condition to enter the Liſts, went to the Field, but found another Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion already engag'd; for the Count <hi>de Fieſque</hi> was return'd more amorous than ever, and tho' their proceedings had given juſt reaſons for a perpetual quarrel on both ſides, Madam <hi>de Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onne</hi> and he no ſooner met, but they were reconcil'd, neither had the Duke reaſon to queſtion it, for being well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted in the Family, they ſuffer'd him to go up without notice, and finding no body in the Chamber, he look'd through the Key-hole, and ſaw an Engagement that would not have ſurpriz'd him had he not known of the Quarrel: Nevertheleſs, altho' he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42116:23"/> came for the ſame purpoſe, and had no reaſon to be contented that the place was already taken, he plac'd himſelf calmly upon a Stool, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well that the Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> who was no rude player, would have ſoon finiſhed the Game; and it was no ſooner over but they both came into the Chamber, full of confuſion at the ſurpriſe to ſee one there they ſo little expected, and whom they could ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſent for upon this occaſion. The Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> thinking that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence would augment the diſorder he perceiv'd they were in, endeavour'd to break it; and as there was nothing but Debauchery in his intentions, he ſoon recover'd the accident, and found himſelf in a more free and eaſie diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of mind than he could have been, had his heart had the leaſt concern in the adventure. I thought you had been both my Friends, <hi>ſaid he to 'em,</hi> and therefore imagin'd you would not have rejoyc'd without me You know that a Reconcilement is equal to a Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and yet you are partaking the delights of Paradiſe, and make me no invitation. I was never inquiſitive un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til to day, and now I am cur'd of it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42116:23"/> for all my life: how ſottiſh a thing it is to ſee the Pleaſures and Tranſports of others through a Key-hole; and I believe had I not left the Colledge it would have coſt me a mortal ſin: Why do you not leave at leaſt, Madam, <hi>ſays he, addreſſing himſelf to Madam</hi> de Lionne, one of your Women here? 'twould ſerve to fool away the time in expecting you; I give you this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and you have no reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it, this will at leaſt abate their curioſity, and your affairs may chance to fall into the hands of a perſon who will not uſe you ſo well as I.</p>
                  <p>There will always remain a certain confuſion upon the firſt diſcovery of our ſecrets, eſpecialy in a Woman that has the leaſt Modeſty left. The Duke might obſerve this truth in Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> ſhe was more diſordered than before, and I know not if ſhe would have made a worſe Figure had her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band been preſent: her Eyes were caſt down, and if ſhe ever ventur'd to look up, 'twas on the Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> whom ſhe ſeem'd to excite to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; but he was yet in a greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, ſo that finding he had not the ſenſe to draw her out of this accident,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42116:24"/> This is what your folly has been the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of, <hi>ſaid ſhe to the Count,</hi> you ſhut the door againſt my will, and the Duke has no doubt ſeen you buſying with ſome trifle. Excuſe me, Madam, <hi>anſwered the Duke,</hi> it was truly no tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle which I ſaw, except you call that ſo which we eſteem the greateſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but bluſh not for it, the Count is very well worth your care, and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you only to acknowledge, that the pleaſure is quite another thing after a little falling out.</p>
                  <p>Whilſt this was ſaying, Madam <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> came in, and drew her Mother from this diſorder; for the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> who, tho' he had not a great paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for her, took pleaſure in her conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, went with her to the Ruel, and afforded an opportunity to theſe Lovers to recover themſelves. Madam <hi>de Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onne,</hi> who had an ambitious heart, that is to ſay, whom one Lover could not ſuffice, was no ſooner free from one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude than ſhe fell into another; and tho' ſhe had promis'd to aſſiſt the Duke, yet ſhe fancied her Daughter gave too much attention to him; and ſhe liſtned after every word he ſpoke, to find if ſhe was not in the right.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:42116:24"/>
                  <p>The Count <hi>de Fieſque</hi> obſerv'd her diſtraction, and quarrel'd with her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, but it was impoſſible for him to interrupt her deſign; ſhe perceiv'd it was e'en as ſhe imagin'd, and ſhe no longer doubted of her tenderneſs, when ſhe found ſhe permitted him to kiſs her Hand without any violence. The Duke immediatly after it went out, upon which ſhe preſum'd the affair was much advanc'd, and that no queſtion it was an earneſt of a more acceptable Promiſe; ſhe reſolv'd if it was ſo, to croſs theſe Lovers with all her power; and having got rid of the Count, ſent for a Chair, pretending buſineſs, yet would not ſtir till the Horſes were in her Daughter's Coach; when ſhe went out, diſperſing her Footmen on ſleeveleſs errands: hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus far proceeded, ſhe bid the Chair-men ſtop at the corner of the Street, commanding them to follow the Coach when it came forth. They were not long in ambuſcade before they ſaw it, the Coach went to the <hi>Tuilleries</hi> near the King's Stables, and ſhe was there almoſt as ſoon as her Daughter.</p>
                  <p>She was ſo diſguis'd, that ſhe hop'd no body would know her; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, miſtruſting her Shape and Air
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42116:25"/> might be remarkable, ſhe counterfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf lame, and follow'd as faſt as ſhe could. The Marchioneſs <hi>de Coeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres</hi> took two turns to loſe ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhe found there, and afterwards went by the Gate towards the <hi>Ponte Rouge,</hi> which oblig'd her Mother to double her pace; and as there was ſome diſtance between 'em, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for her to arrive there ſo ſoon as ſhe deſir'd, ſo that when ſhe came to the Gate, her Daughter was already out of ſight; ſhe look'd about on all ſides to ſee if ſhe could perceive which way ſhe went, but all that ſhe could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover was a Coach without a Livery, which in a moment was out of ſight: ſhe was vex'd there was none ready to follow it, and reſolv'd not to be trap'd ſo the next time, not doubting, if her ſuſpicions were true, that theſe Lovers would not be contented with this ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview.</p>
                  <p>It was not eaſie to deceive her, ſhe was too knowing in this matter, for even in this Coach were the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the Duke; he was carrying her to <hi>Autheuil,</hi> a Houſe which the Mareſchal <hi>de Grancey</hi> hir'd for <hi>du Meſnil,</hi> and ſhe had given him leave to make uſe of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42116:25"/> when he pleas'd. No ſooner were they arriv'd, but he had a mind to know if he was ſtill enchanted; and he found that two or three days of reſt to a Man of his Age, was a wonderful remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch ſort of Charms; when he had careſs'd her twice he was glad to entertain her with ſome other diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and he thought nothing was more pleaſant than the relation of what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to him with her Mother. The Marchioneſs told him there could be nothing of it, for ſhe was too much fix'd to the Count <hi>de Fieſque</hi> to make an eſſay of his ſorce; but the Story not being very much to his advantage, and he aſſuring it with many horrid Oaths, ſhe would rather believe it than occaſion further Imprecations.</p>
                  <p>She had nevertheleſs ſome other tokens of the truth of it, which ſhe would have contentedly paſs'd without, for the Duke ſhe found was again en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted; the Marchioneſs <hi>de Coeuvres,</hi> who was one of the prettieſt Women in <hi>Paris,</hi> took it for a great affront to her, and began to be concern'd; ſhe not only ſhew'd it by her Countenance, but reſented it in theſe terms; I was never a Glutton in this point, and if
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42116:26"/> you knew what Monſieur <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> ſays of me concerning it, you would find it was not on that occaſion that I ſpeak; beſides, it is often a great puniſhment to me to endure it, which makes him often ſay, that I am not my Mothers Daughter, and that certainly I was chang'd at Nurſe. Yet altho' my cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might have diſcouraged him, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave me ſuch an affront as you have done. I remember that on our Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Night — but why ſhould I tell you, it will make you dye with ſhame, and yet he was a Husband, but you a Gallant. But ye Gods what a Gallant? one that has taken that Name to abuſe me, and I may judge by this firſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, what I muſt expect from you; but it is well I have not been long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, there is a remedy, and I know what Courſe I ought to take. The Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> who was not naturally very baſhful, was nevertheleſs aſham'd at theſe reprimands, and beg'd of Madam <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> to expoſe all her Beauties to his ſight, aſſuring her it would be a perfect recovery to his Vigour.</p>
                  <p>Many if they had been in her place, would have granted a requeſt like this, but whether ſhe was miſtruſtful of her
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42116:26"/> hidden Beauties, or ſhe imagin'd it to little purpoſe, ſhe would not conſent to it, ſo that from the firſt they were not very much Charm'd with one another.</p>
                  <p>Parting in this indifferency, it was ſome time before they had another meeting, which troubl'd Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who was in pain to be aſſur'd of their Intrigue; what ſhe had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd made her not queſtion their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, but thought they were too cunning for her, and the vexation at it put her upon the deſign of adverti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Marqueſs <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> to look narrowly after the Conduct of his Wife. The Marqueſs was ſo mean ſpirited, that he reſolv'd to call all the Family together upon this affair: Every one was invited, even to the Grandfather the Mareſchal, and his quality and age giving him without diſpute the firſt place in the Council, he gave attention to all that was ſaid, without diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his own Sentiments. Moſt of 'em were for ſending the Marchioneſs to a Nunnery, ſaying this was what might be expected from ſo unequal a Match, that if their Relation had marry'd one of equal rank to himſelf, he had had no occaſion to demand Juſtice now.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42116:27"/> Some enlarg'd upon it, and ſaid, that an ill Tree ſeldom brings good Fruit; and when her Mother had always made profeſſion of Gallantry, it was not to be expected, but her Daughter ſhould reſemble her. That they had Whores enough in the Family without her, and that it was fit ſhe ſhould not only be ſent to the Nunnery, but alſo be depriv'd of ever bearing the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
                  <p>The good Mareſchal had a Colour at this Diſcourſe, and they who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark'd it, believ'd that it was occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by his Reſentment of it, or through ſome new indiſpoſition that had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to him. But when they had done ſpeaking, they ſoon perceiv'd there was nothing of this in it; neither could they doubt of it, when they heard him ſay, In troth you make me mad to hear ye talk thus; ye that pretend to be ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate, but who had not been here any more than my ſelf, had our Mothers been ſo nice. We know what we know, but you may be certain that the fineſt of our Noſes was borrowed from our Neighbours, and we have ſo much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to praiſe the good Women of our Family, both in the direct and collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42116:27"/> Line, that I admire ye are for ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing thoſe who reſemble 'em. When I marry'd my Grandſon <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> to Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> do you imagine I did it in conſideration, either becauſe ſhe was the Daughter of a Miniſter of State, or becauſe ſhe was rich, or for her Reputation; theſe were too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row proſpects for a man of my age, and experience; no, my drift was, that being ſo handſom, ſhe might revive the luſtre and greatneſs of our Family, which always drew its conſiderableneſs not from the Males, but Females. If I have been deceiv'd, it was not my fault, my Intentions were as well meant in this, as in my marriage with <hi>Mademoiſelle de Manicamp,</hi> in effect my Wife was handſom enough to make all our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, but her Brothers Reputation has been a great injury to her. I know there was a Propoſition made to her, before I marryed her, which ſhe did not think agreeable, being of a diſpoſition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to her Brother; Since that time a thing of the ſame nature has happen'd to her, but ſhe had rather dye than not be conformable to the Family ſhe is enter'd into. How has ſhe wander'd from the Footſteps of our Anceſtors?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42116:28"/> for if ſo, I declare my ſelf her greateſt Enemy. Has ſhe had any Commerce with the Chevalier <hi>de Lorrain?</hi> Let her be burnt: Has ſhe had any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with the Chevalier <hi>de Chaſtillon?</hi> Drown her: Has ſhe had any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh?</hi> Let her be hang'd: If you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her of this, you need not ſeek any other Executioner. But if her Crime has been only to ſeek the Pleaſures of Nature, I declare my ſelf her Protector. Let all this be kept ſecret amongſt our ſelves, that the Court know nothing of it; The ſhorteſt Follies are the beſt, and it will be ill husbandry to let the whole Town laugh at our Expence. The whole Company were offended at the beginning of this Diſcourſe, but they found ſo much good Senſe in the Concluſion, that they reſolv'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to it. There was not time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver their opinion of it, for a Lacquy coming in to acquaint the Mareſchal that <hi>Leſſé du Bail</hi> and two or three other famous Gameſters expected him, he took his leave, telling them they ought not by any means to diſſent from what he had declar'd.</p>
                  <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Laon</hi> when his Father
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42116:28"/> was gone, remain'd the Preſident of the Council, and being very Politick, thinking Monſieur <hi>de Lionnes</hi> favour would do him no diſſervice in obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cardinal's Cap, which he has ſince accompliſhed; he told 'em, he extreamly wonder'd at two things, firſt that they ſhould proceed thus againſt his Niece upon a meer ſuſpition; and ſecondly ſhould ſo raſhly ſpeak ill of his Family; that for the one, it ought to be made out as clear as the Sun at Noon, before they went ſo far; and for the other, it was very well known that the Family of <hi>Lionne</hi> was as renown'd as any in <hi>Dauphiné.</hi> That the Malice of thoſe who denyed a matter ſo authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſufficiently demonſtrated how little Faith was to be given to 'em in other things; that Madam <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed too handſom to be without Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; but on the other ſide, ſhe was too wiſe to make a return to their Paſſions. That whilſt he had been at <hi>Paris,</hi> he was often enough with her, to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice if there had been any irregularity in her Conduct, but he had never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd her guilty of any thing to the diſcredit of her Family; that he would look more nicely to it now, and would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42116:29"/> be ſo much with her when his affairs would permit, that there ſhould none be more capable of giving a better judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her than himſelf. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> thought he was oblig'd to give him thanks for the pains he would take, and making his Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, told him, there were few Uncles to be found ſo kind to take the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of their Relations ſo much to heart. But he was the only man in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany who did not penetrate his Deſign. The good Prelate was fal'n in Love with his Niece, and having not leiſure enough to follow the whole Duty of a Lover, he reſolv'd to make her eſteem this as a great piece of Service, and to demand an immediate recompence for it; in effect, no ſooner was the Aſſembly broke up, when he went to the Marchioneſs, and looking upon her in an Air that would have diſcovered his Intentions, had ſhe obſerv'd it. I know not Madam, <hi>ſays he,</hi> if you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perceiv'd the extream Paſſion I have for you, ſhould I have acquainted you with it the moment I was ſenſible of it, it would have been divulg'd the firſt time I ſaw you; but thoſe kind of Declarations are only proper for Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42116:29"/> and for my part, I always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd that before we advanc'd ſo far, the perſon was to be prepar'd by ſome conſiderable Services. If you have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd my proceedings, I have omitted no opportunity, but they have always been ſo frivolous in Compariſon of what I coveted, that hitherto I have not had the boldneſs to diſcover my ſelf. But opportunity to day has preſented, and I have appeas'd a whole Family incens'd againſt you, and who talk'd of nothing leſs than confineing you perpetually to a Nunnery. I knew, Madam, they were doing a great injuſtice to you, but it had paſs'd irrecoverably, had not I engag'd for you; this would deſerve a recompence to another, but for my part it will be ſatisfaction enough to me, will you but only give me leave to ſee you, and to love you. The Marchioneſs <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> was ſo aſtoniſh'd at this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, that ſhe could ſcarcely believe her Ears, and the ſurpriſe of what ſhe heard was ſo great, that it interrupted her as ſhe was going to ſhew her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment to his boldneſs, ſo that ſhe fell from the paſſion ſhe was rais'd to, and calmly demanded what could be the occaſion, or what had ſhe ever done to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42116:30"/> be ſo baſely us'd? I cannot tell you, Madam, <hi>anſwer'd the Biſhop,</hi> except it proceeds from ſome ſuſpicions of your Husbands; he mentions no particular Circumſtance, and all that I can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in it, is, that ſome body who has no good Wiſhes for you, has oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd this miſchief betwixt you. But fear nothing, he depends now altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Character I ſhall give him of your Conduct, and I have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to watch you ſo narrowly, that it is impoſſible for any thing to ſcape unknown to me. Hereupon he gave her an account of what was ſaid in the Aſſembly, except what the good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal ſpoke in her favour, for he would have all the obligation of clearing her from this Affair attributed to himſelf.</p>
                  <p>The Marchioneſs was overjoy'd that nothing of her Intrigue was diſcover'd, and taking courage upon it, I am very unhappy, Sir, <hi>ſays ſhe,</hi> to be ſo unjuſtly accus'd; and tho' I cannot diſown ſome Obligation to you in it, yet give me leave to tell you, that ſuch proceedings as yours will quickly leſſen the favour: You ought to remember your own Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, and the Family we are of, if you forget my Virtue, and the Duty
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42116:30"/> I owe my Husband; but I find the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generous reaſon of it, the injurious Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries you have heard of me, has encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd you to this boldneſs, but I ſhould have more reaſon to have better thoughts of you, had you not baſely concluded, that (tho' I had an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to Crimes of that nature,) I was of ſo ſear'd a Conſcience not to abhor what you propoſe. 'Tis not any Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal matter I propoſe to you, anſwer'd the Biſhop, and you do me wrong to accuſe me of it. What is it that you demand of me then? <hi>Says Madam de Coeuvres.</hi> Only that you permit me to adore you, and to ſeek all occaſions of rendring you ſervice, <hi>reply'd the Biſhop.</hi> What, 'tis a trifle then with you, <hi>ſays Madam de Coeuvres,</hi> for a Biſhop to make Love to a marryed Woman, and for an Uncle to endeavour to ſeduce his Niece? Believe me, if I have any Caſe of Conſcience to conſult of, you ſhall never be my Caſuiſt; in the mean time, tho' I cannot forbid you ſeeing of me, ſince it is not in my power to hinder you, yet oblige me ſo far as not to offer any ſuch Diſcourſe to me, for perhaps I ſhall not have diſcretion enough to conceal it from Monſieur <hi>de Coeuvres.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe words were Thunderbolts to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42116:31"/> the Biſhop, and for all his Wit he was ſo daſh'd, that he had not a word to ſay. A poor unfortunate Prieſt, that came a Moment after to ſolicit ſome ſmall buſineſs with him, found the Effects of his anger, and all his people found him in ſo ill temper, that they could not imagin the reaſon of ſo great an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. They ſuffer'd for it as well as himſelf. At Table every thing was ſo ill dreſs'd, that he ask'd if they deſign'd to poiſon him; and if he durſt, he would have beaten the whole World. His Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was not nevertheleſs extinguiſh'd, the difficulty had rather increas'd it; but not daring to mention it any more to the Marchioneſs, diſcourag'd by his reception, he reſolv'd to be ſo diligent a ſpy upon her Conduct, that fear might force her to that, which he could not obtain from her Love.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Argus,</hi> with all his care, could not diſcover any thing for ſome time, and tho' the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> came con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to the Houſe, there being an intimacy imagin'd between him and Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> and he asking moſt commonly for her, it paſs'd ſo well, that this was the man he leaſt ſuſpected, but it being difficult to deceive a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver long, the Biſhop after a while fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cv'd
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42116:31"/> that Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> was only the pretence, but that the Sacrifice was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for the Marchioneſs. The Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> who had not yet found an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to reconcile himſelf to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem <hi>de Lionne,</hi> was ſeeking all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for it, which was the reaſon he ſo often viſited her, and at the firſt that preſented, knowing her temper and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, Madam, <hi>ſays he,</hi> behold a Criminal, who comes to do himſelf Juſtice, and tho' I have ſome reaſon to accuſe you, yet I being the firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, am oblig'd to make the firſt Submiſſion, to authoriſe my following reſentment. What do you complain of, Sir, anſwer'd ſhe, is it becauſe you found me with Monſieur <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> how did it concern you, and after what I have ſeen, would you again abuſe me? The Duke thinking ſhe reproach'd him with his Impotency, I have nothing to ſay to it, Madam, <hi>anſwered he,</hi> and I have already acknowledg'd my ſelf the moſt Criminal of Manking, but there is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs for all Crimes, and here I am ready to repair the Injury. At theſe words he was making ready to perform his promiſe, and altho' Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> was not accuſtom'd to refuſe any body, ſhe told him in a deſpiſing air, that he was
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42116:32"/> miſtaken, and ſhe was not Madam <hi>de Coeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres.</hi> What do you mean, Madam, <hi>anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Duke,</hi> and why do you mention one who thinks not of us, and we have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think of? Do you take me for a Fool, <hi>cry'd</hi> Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> did not I ſee her with you the other day? I follow'd you to the <hi>Tuilleries,</hi> and tho' the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Coach was diſguis'd, it hinder'd not me from diſcovering the whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue. You ſaw it, Madam, <hi>demanded the Duke</hi> de Saux <hi>with a ſerious Countenance?</hi> Yes, Sir, <hi>anſwered Madam</hi> de Lionne, with my own Eyes. Since it is ſo, then Madam, ſays he very ſeriouſly, give me your hand, we have nothing to reproach one the other withal, and I have ſeen as well as you thoſe things; it will be to little purpoſe to remention, remember not the Coach, and I'le indeavour to forget the Cloſet; what ſay you, is it not very reaſonable? this was too Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier an Entertainment, to win any ſavours from the Lady, ſo that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Diſcourſe, they parted ſo Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, that each imagin'd there was nothing after this to be demanded. The Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> returned home, and was there hardly a quarter of an Hour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he receiv'd this Note from the Marchioneſs <hi>de Coeuvres.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:42116:32"/>
                        <head>A Letter from Madam <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> to the Duke <hi>de Saux.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>IT is not above an hour or two ſince I deſign'd to enquire how you did after your paralitick fit, but when I ſaw you get into your Coach ſo overjoy'd at Madam</hi> de Lionnes, <hi>I thought my Complement would be to little purpoſe. Any beſides my ſelf would have wonder'd, that ſhe ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form a Miracle, they had ſo unſucceſsful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour'd to Compaſs; but I find the reaſon; in many things, I have not an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience equal to hers; and perhaps ſhe may have an intereſt with the Saints, that I cannot boaſt of; Let me know which you are beholden to, for I have all the reaſon in the World to believe it proceeds from a Religious Effect, when I find you pay ſuch Devotion to Relicks.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>This quarrel did not at all ſurpriſe the Duke, and the Count <hi>de Tallard</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Country for ſome time, and <hi>Loiiiſon d' Arquien</hi> ſick through too much Devotion, he ſinding himſelf in a humour not to be pleas'd any longer without Company, return'd her this Anſwer.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> to Madam <hi>de Coeuvres.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>IF I was at Madam</hi> de Lionnes, <hi>'twas with a deſign to ſee you, but perſons
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42116:33"/> of your temper are not pitiful every day, and 'tis enough for us, if, knowing that we dye for you, you are but pleas'd at our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Fates. I have been in ſearch for you ever ſince my misfortune, to let you know 'tis you alone can cure me; if you will make an Experiment of it about two in the Morning, I have an infallible ſecret will help me to the door of your Apartment. Be ſatisfy'd you run no danger, ſince your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band will not return from</hi> Verſailles <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to morrow Night; if you have but the leaſt conſideration for my health, you will accept the offer; remember that old miſchiefs are dangerous, and if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit mine to root it ſelf deeper, have a care leſt it becomes at laſt incurable.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Madam <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> was not ſo angry, but a propoſition of this nature had power to appeaſe her, ſhe therefore bid the Meſſenger tell him ſhe expected him. The Mercury returning to the Duke's Appartment overjoy'd, obſerv'd not that the Biſhop <hi>de Laon</hi> was writing a Letter in the Duke's Cloſet, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to the door, cry'd, good News, good News; the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> made him Signs to hold his tongue, but this was enough for the ſmoaky Biſhop,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42116:33"/> and his ſuſpicions were doubled when he found him to be the Dukes Agent in Love Affairs. He could make no certain Judgment of it, but ſuſpecting it might be ſome appointment for night, he reſolv'd to watch ſo ſtrictly that he ſhould be ſure to know if his Niece was concern'd in it. And the Duke who was very indiſcreet, had often let fall ſome Words, which convinc'd him he had not ſo much eſteem for Madam <hi>de Lionnes,</hi> as to render her ſuch frequent Viſits. After he left the Duke, he was impatient till Night came, that he might place himſelf in Ambuſcade; and altho' there could be no greater diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to him, than to find what he was in ſearch of, yet his whole hopes were engag'd upon the diſcovery of the Myſtery. The hour he wiſh'd for being arriv'd, he play'd the ſpy round the <hi>Hoſtel de Lionne,</hi> and that he might be ſure not to be deceiv'd, he look'd in every ones face that paſſed by: This was a fine Employment for a Biſhop, and eſpecially ſo ſerious a one as he ſeem'd; but he took what care he could to avoid the Scandal, having left his Croſs at home, and cover'd his bald Crown with a Peruque, with his Sword by his ſide, he ſeem'd to be no little Cavalier.</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:42116:34"/>
                  <p>Such was the power of Love: but it was not in his head alone, for the good man Mr. <hi>de Lionne,</hi> notwithſtanding all his buſineſs, and his age, was no freer from it than the reſt. Whether it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for a man to live without a Woman, or whether he thought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his Wife at a Miſtreſs, he had one who was an honeſt Citizens Wife, and whilſt her Husband was buſie in an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment he had given him, to draw him from home, he us'd to refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with her, from the burdenſom af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs which the Kings us'd to truſt him withal. It happen'd that this Night he had juſt left her, and as he was return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a <hi>Valet</hi> that us'd to aſſiſt him in his Amour; the Biſhop, who thought every body was the Duke de <hi>Saux,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd to look in his face. The <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> taking him for a Thief, clapp'd a Piſtol he had under his Cloak to his breaſt. The Biſhop, whoſe trade it was not to be ſtout, taking likewiſe the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> for a Rogue, deſir'd him not to kill him, and if it was only his Purſe that he wanted, he was ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it. He us'd to be often at <hi>M— de Lionne's,</hi> ſo that they both quickly knew him by his Voice, and the <hi>Valet</hi>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:42116:34"/> ſurpris'd, told him he need not fear, for that was his Maſter <hi>de Lionne.</hi> Mr. <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who deſir'd not to be known, was angry that the imprudence of the <hi>Valet</hi> had diſcover'd him, but it being paſt redreſs, and knowing the Biſhop by his Voice, he ask'd him for what Adventure he was thus diſguis'd. The good Prelate was in deſpair at this rencounter, and tho' he was reported to be of a ready wit, he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in great confuſion, he would have deny'd himſelf if he could, but Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi> and his Servant knew his Face and Voice too well for that, in ſpight of the diſguiſe, and the latter was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready asking his pardon for preſenting the Piſtol to him, ſaying it was to be excus'd, ſince it was impoſſible for any body to know him in that diſguiſe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Excuſes gave the Prelate time to recover himſelf, and confeſſing part of the Truth to Mr. <hi>de Lionne,</hi> that he was come ſo accouter'd to ſee if the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> would come there, whom he ſuſpected had an Intrigue with the Marchioneſs <hi>de Coeuvres;</hi> he reſerv'd the other part, which was nevertheleſs the true occaſion of the trouble he gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Mr. <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who knew the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42116:35"/> of Humane Nature, and who had no ſevere opinion of his Daughter, commended his zeal, and proffer'd to watch with him: So that the <hi>Valet</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent away, whom the Biſhop did not think fit to be privy to this Secret. They agreed to ſeparate in order to make the better diſcoveries; but their pains would have been to little purpoſe, had not the natural inquiſitiveneſs of the <hi>Valet</hi> engag'd him to ſtay alſo to ſee what all this matter meant.</p>
                  <p>As he was looking attentively about, he perceiv'd a Man ſcaling the Garden Walls, which the Sentinels could not ſee, they happening to be on the other ſide; from thence he diſcern'd him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Window open'd for him, which anſwer'd to the Mount, and this threw him into a profound Meditation. He thought there muſt be Love in the caſe, and not knowing how to apply it to any body except his Miſtreſs or her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he was in diſpute whether he ſhould acquaint his Maſter with it, doubting if the news would be agreeable to him. Whil'ſt he was thus reaſoning upon what he was oblig'd to do, the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> who was the Man that went in, was endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to get into the Marchioneſs <hi>de
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42116:35"/> Coeuvres</hi> Apartment, not far off; but he found himſelf ſtop'd by the arm, by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who had made an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment with the Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> and imagin'd it to be him: Is it you, <hi>ſaid ſhe at the ſame time,</hi> my dear Count! why did you ſtay ſo long?</p>
                  <p>The Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> who very well knew Madem <hi>de Lionnes</hi> voice, made no reply, which very much ſurpris'd her, fearing ſhe was in a miſtake; to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, ſhe threw her arms about his neck, and finding him bigger, and fatter than the friend ſhe expected, ſhe ſhriek'd out loud enough to have wak'd all the Houſe, had they not been in a dead ſleep. The Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> apprehenſive leſt her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence ſhould occaſion miſchief on both ſides, broke the ſilence in theſe terms, which he uttered as ſoftly as poſſible. What do you do, Madam, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> have you not the judgment to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you are going to ruin your ſelf? If it was my own concern alone, I ſhould ſay nothing, but eſcape as well as I could, but what will your Husband ſay, what excuſes can you make, to perſwade him this appointment came not from you.</p>
                  <p>Theſe words, and the Voice which was known to Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> made
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42116:36"/> her reflect upon the reaſonableneſs of what was ſaid. What, is it you then, Monſieur <hi>le</hi> Duke, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> what do you come here for? I won't deceive you, Madam, <hi>anſwer'd he,</hi> I did not look for you, no more than you expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me: And therefore give me leave to continue my Adventure, leſt I inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt yours, and 'tis after this faſhion, people like us ſhould live in this Age. The propoſition was very honeſt, and reaſonable, but whether ſhe had a mind to make tryal of him, or whether the time that ſhe expected the Count being Elapſed, it was inſupportable to her to paſs the night alone. No, no, Sir, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed ſhe,</hi> it ſhall not go as you imagine, I know it is my Daughter you would be at, but let it diſpleaſe you both if it will, I ſhall nevertheleſs make uſe of the opportunity, ſince it has offer'd it ſelf ſo kindly; in all likelyhood the Charm of the <hi>Pulvillio</hi> may be broken, and you muſt give me proofs of it this very inſtant.</p>
                  <p>After theſe words which were ſpoke in a very low Voice, leſt any body ſhould over-hear, ſhe would have led him to her Chamber; but he not able to conſent to the change, Ah, Madam,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42116:36"/> 
                     <hi>ſaid he,</hi> whilſt he was dragging along almoſt by force, I have promis'd Madam <hi>de Coeuvres</hi> to come to her, I dare not break my word, give me but only leave to go and diſengage my ſelf, and I will return immediately upon my word, and give you all manner of ſatisfaction. The Lady was not ſo credulous to truſt him; and as ſhe had try'd his ſtrength, and found it not ſufficient to be divided, ſhe would not by any means part with him; and he on his ſide continuing obſtinate, ſhe propos'd a medium, which was to go her ſelf, and fetch her Daughter. He accepted the propoſition, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to get out of her hands by any other means; but before ſhe went, ſhe conducted him to her Chamber, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging him to go to bed, and promiſing to bring her Daughter, bidding him take care how he behaved himſelf, ſince he was to paſs that night between 'em. If the Duke had been too ſcrupulous, ſuch a propoſition would have ſtartled him, but he being a Courtier fear'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this nature; but anſwer'd, that he ſhould expect 'em with great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, and that it was a long time ſince he had made uſe of any <hi>Pulvillio.</hi> The Lady would have willingly made
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42116:37"/> tryal at that moment if he ſpoke truth, but he not agreeing to it, ſhe went to fetch her Daughter, who was very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly waiting for the Duke. This made her not at all ſurpris'd to hear ſome body walking in her Anti-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but ſhe was very much ſtartled, when, inſtead of him, ſhe perceiv'd her Mother. Had not Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> fear'd the loſing of time, ſhe would have ask'd her the occaſion of her ſitting up ſo late, and what ſhe was waiting for; but it being very dear to her, ſhe ask'd her no unprofitable queſtions. In fine, all the Complement was, that ſhe muſt come into her Chamber, for ſhe had ſomething of great conſequence to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to her.</p>
                  <p>Tho' the Command was poſitive, Madam <hi>de Coeuvres,</hi> affraid of loſing her appointment, endeavour'd to excuſe her ſelf; but her Mother deſiring her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, aſſuring her it was for her good, ſhe at laſt conſented; it was not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs without extraordinary fear, for ſhe could not imagin any thing leſs, than the diſcovery of the whole affair, and 'twas certainly to give her ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice about her Conduct. Theſe thoughts, and the unſeaſonable hour of the night,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42116:37"/> made her follow her Mother in great ſilence and apprehenſion into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where ſhe was very much ſurpris'd to find the Duke in Bed; ſhe was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly very angry with him, believing that he had ſacrific'd her, and was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to diſcharge her paſſion, when Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who found the night ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd, and was unwilling to waſte the remaining part of it, told her as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly as was poſſible, how ſhe had met with the Duke, and what they had agreed upon. This a little appeas'd the young Lady, and tho' ſhe was ſorry to be forc'd to part with a ſhare to her Mother, of what ſhe had all expected to her ſelf, ſhe lik'd it yet much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than to have found the Duke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful. Yet ſhe made ſome difficulties before ſhe conſented to the propoſition; but Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> ſeeing the time conſum'd by 'em, threatning to ruin her if ſhe did not obey, and the Duke Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her on the other ſide, ſhe underſs'd herſelf, half out of obedience, and half through inclination and deſire. Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> was doing the ſame thing on her ſide, and both, expecting good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune that Night, were only in looſe Gowns, which were ſoon taken off, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42116:38"/> one would have thought a reward had been promis'd to thoſe who ſhould be firſt undreſt, ſuch haſte did they ſeem to make.</p>
                  <p>Whilſt this was paſſing within doors, the Biſhop and Monſieur <hi>de Lionne</hi> were ſtill playing the Sentinels without, tho' not with an equal concern, for tho' Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi> was a man of Honour, and allarm'd by the Infamy the Biſhop had diſcover'd to him, he ſuffer'd nothing in compariſon of what was occaſion'd by the Jealouſie of the other. All his thoughts terminated in revenge, and had he been as much a Brother of the Blade as the Church, the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> ſhould have dyed by no other hand than his. Monſieur <hi>de Lionne</hi> being ſeparated from him, for the reaſon I before told you, he had leaſure to entertain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with theſe thoughts, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times flatter'd him, and at other times made him deſpair; and whilſt he was in theſe Meditations, Monſieur <hi>de Lionne,</hi> who was advertis'd by his <hi>Valet</hi> of what he had ſeen, interrupted him, telling him his doubts were but too well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for a man went into the Houſe. Gods <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> ſwore the Biſhop at the ſame time, and do you bear it ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42116:39"/> patiently, as if the affront concern'd not you, as well as me. After he had given Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi> this anſwer, he ask'd the <hi>Valet</hi> what he had ſeen, and he having inform'd him according to what I before mention'd, he again de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi> if he would ſuffer an injury of that nature to go unpuniſh'd. I am of opinion it will be the beſt way, anſwer'd Mr. <hi>de Lionne,</hi> it muſt either be my Wife or my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the leaſt noiſe that I make of it ruins all our Reputations. It will be more prudent to keep the Secret amongſt us three. I know the diſcretion of my <hi>Valet,</hi> and anſwer for his Fidelity. Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi> could not in truth take better meaſures; but the Biſhop who was ſir'd at every word, Gods <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> ſaid he, ſwearing again like any Car-man, 'tis what you deſerve, ſince you can bear the Scandal ſo calmly; but it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſaid that I ſuffer it without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, and as I am perſwaded the matter concerns my Niece, you will not be angry I hope if I have not the like tameneſs; at theſe words he bid the <hi>Valet</hi> who had the Key of a door which was only us'd in his Maſters Amorous Intrigues, to open it immediately, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42116:40"/> Mr. <hi>de Lionnes</hi> honour being touch'd, he follow'd him rather out of complaiſance, than inclination.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Valet de Chambre</hi> having obſerv'd after the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> went over the wall what became of him, he had taken notice of the Management of the two Ladies, and knowing poſitively in what Chamber they were, he carry'd his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and the Biſhop directly thither, when <hi>de Lionne</hi> had fetch'd a double Key which he had to all the Apartments. The Duke and the two Ladies were ſo buſily employ'd, that they heard not the door open, ſo that they were taken as <hi>Moſs caught his Mare.</hi> Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> threw her ſelf at her Husband's feet, promiſing ſhe would never do ſo again whilſt ſhe liv'd. The Marchioneſs <hi>de Coeuvres,</hi> who was in no leſs confuſion, knew not what to ſay for her ſelf, but getting near the Biſhop, who was for ruining all, Do not ruin my Reputation, ſaid ſhe, appeaſe but my Father, and hide this from my Husband, and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you not to be ungrateful. Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi> was ſo ſurpris'd at the novelty of the Frolick, that he ſaid not one word. He thought himſelf a Cuckold, but to ſind a Spark between the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42116:40"/> and the Daughter, ſeem'd ſo ſtrange a thing to him, that he could not have more wondred, had the horns ſprouted out immediately on his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. All that he could ſay, was, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Wife, unfortunate Daughter, to which they return'd no anſwer.</p>
                  <p>The Biſhops anger was in the mean time very much abated by thoſe gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den promiſes, and eager in purſuit of 'em. I think, <hi>ſays he coldly to Mr. de Lionne,</hi> you had a great deal of reaſon when you advis'd us not to dive fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into our inſamy. The leſs noiſe the better in theſe matters, as you ſay, and if you will take my opinion let us proceed no farther, it is ſufficient that we know what we do, without acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Town with it. This advice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conformable to Mr. <hi>de Lionne</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, was follow'd, ſo that the Duke had liberty to withdraw, and as brave as he was, he was not a little glad to ſee himſelf ſafe out of their hands. After this the Biſhop, under a pretence of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his Niece, led her to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where demanding her promiſe, ſhe durſt not refuſe him, for fear he ſhould ruin her with her Husband, and the whole Family. And having obtain'd what
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42116:41"/> he deſir'd, knowing ſhe did it only out of fear, imagin'd ſhe would quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to her firſt Affections; and to prevent it, he manag'd the affairs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that method with her Husband, that ſhe was ſent into the Country to a Seat of his, not far from the Biſhops. This produc'd a good effect, for he recided more conſtantly than uſual in his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. This little Commerce laſted for a year or two, when affairs of State cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him out of the Kingdom, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion took the place of Love, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd an Inceſt, the Marchioneſs would never have conſented to, but in defence of her Reputation.</p>
                  <p>As for Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band not enduring the ſight of her, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd her to a Religious houſe, which made the Publick cenſure, tho' no one doubted but it was for ſome Love In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue; For the Lady had the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of being frail, in which the World was not deceiv'd; yet every one deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be aſſur'd of the report, the Duke <hi>de Saux</hi> took care to let them know it. He publiſh'd himſelf his own Adventure, chuſing rather to be tax'd with indiſcretion, than be depriv'd of the pleaſure of talking. The noiſe of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42116:41"/> it being ſpread about <hi>Paris,</hi> the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture was found ſo new, that it was the ſubject of all Converſation for ſome time, which gave occaſion to one of the Court to make a Lampoon upon it.</p>
                  <p>And thus ends the Intrigue of the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> with Madam <hi>de Lionne</hi> and her Daughter. The firſt remaining in Religion whilſt her Husband liv'd, is become ſo old, that ſhe is forced to be contented with the Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> who out of neceſſity is oblig'd to paſs by many things which would not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to a more Critical Lover. As for the Daughter whether he has had ſome ſecret advice of her Intrigue, or whether ſhe be naturally unconſtant, ſhe ſeems not to be much concern'd at it, paſſing moſt of her time in the Country.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:42116:42"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42116:42"/>
                  <p>THE HISTORY OF THE MARESCHALLESS DE LA FERTE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. R.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old Bailey.</hi> 1690.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="novel">
                  <pb facs="tcp:42116:43"/>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:42116:43"/>
                  <head>THE HISTORY OF THE Mareſchalleſs de la Ferté.</head>
                  <p>WHat I have told you of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> ſhews a great condeſcention in one who had aſpired to Charm even the King; yet it is nothing in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of what I am going to relate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Mareſchalleſs <hi>de la Ferté,</hi> who is my other Heroeſs; but one ſo Illuſtrious, that it would be difficult to find her fellow, ſhould you ſeek through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Paris,</hi> which is nevertheleſs a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous place for ſuch kind of Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries. However, ſhe was no ſooner thrown from the aſpiring hopes I have before mention'd, but ſhe began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42116:44"/> to comfort her ſelf: And it ſeem'd not difficult, ſince he who made her forget ſo Charming an Idea, was not one of extraordinary merit. She was of a good Family, and the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchal prov'd himſelf more couragious when he marry'd her, than he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore done by all the Warlike enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he had ever attempted. For ſhe muſt either have been chang'd at nurſe, or reſemble the reſt of her Relations who were ſo inclin'd: a fair Example whereof was to be ſeen in her Siſter the Counteſs <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> whom <hi>Buſſy</hi> has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to render famous to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, tho' he has very much fail'd in it. The Copy falling ſo ſhort of the Original. This Lady, tho' of an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Beauty, and far beneath her Siſters, had nevertheleſs ſo good an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of her ſelf, that ſhe thought it her right to Charm all the World. Her Husband the moſt brutal Man that ever was, not doubting but he had run a great riſque in marrying her, made her a Souldierly Compliment the day after the Wedding, by Heaven, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> now you are my Wife, and you do eſteem it I am confident no little fortune for you, but let me
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42116:44"/> adviſe you in good time, that if you intend to reſemble your Siſter, and ſome other of your Relations of the ſame value, you will find it your ruin. The Lady who had taken his brutality during the Night for an exceſs of Love, was undeceiv'd at theſe Words, and as he paſs'd in the eſteem of the World, for one that would not ſuffer any rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, ſhe for ſome time conſin'd her ſelf, tho' not without offering great violence to her temper and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>The Employments he had in the war, occaſioning his abſence a great part of the year, afforded her many opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to deceive him. But he had taken ſuch care by placing thoſe near her who were carefully to obſerve her, that it was impoſſible for her to make one falſe ſtep without his knowledge. At his departure, he charg'd her not to ſee the Counteſs <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> fearing ſuch ill Company, together with her own conſtitution, of which he was now particularly acquainted, might aſſiſt to corrupt her. The Counteſs who knew of this Countermand, was concern'd to death at it, pretending that it injur'd her Reputation in the Opinion of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42116:45"/> World, more than her own Conduct. And as Revenge is commonly the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſin of Women; ſhe could not reſt till ſhe had plac'd him in the ſame rank with her own Husband, that is, till ſhe had contriv'd a pair of Horns for him. Having diſcover'd her intentions in this to the Marqueſs of <hi>Beuvron</hi> who lov'd her, ſhe deſir'd him to render her that ſervice, in hopes, that being both handſom and witty, it would not be difficult for him to ſupplant a Jealous Coxcomb, who could never have pleas'd her Siſter any other way than by making her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>De Beuvron</hi> in this, was like the Duke <hi>de Saux,</hi> he had not been ſo nice to have ſcrupl'd the Inceſt, had the Lady pleas'd him; but imagining the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was made to him only to get rid of him, and give a better oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to the Duke <hi>de Candalle,</hi> of whom he began to be jealous, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it ſo ill, that the Counteſs ſoon perceiv'd, ſhe muſt addreſs her ſelf to another, if ſhe intended to proſper, in her deſign. To rely upon one ſhe knew not in ſo critical an Affair, and was not aſſur'd of, was to run a great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and occaſion Diſcourſes which
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:42116:45"/> might not have been very agreeable; and as ſhe had not then abandon'd her ſelf to ſuch an infinite number as ſhe has ſince done, ſhe was very much troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on whom to make choice; and in ſine, after ſhe had very much thought of it, ſhe fixt upon her own Husband, in whom ſhe fancy'd, ſhe had heretofore obſerv'd ſome kind looks towards her Siſter, by which ſhe concluded her not indifferent to him; and beſides ſhe thought it not ill Policy to amuſe him with ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, that he might not pry ſo narrowly after her affairs. She was not at all deceiv'd in his inclinations, he would have willingly chang'd her for the Mareſchalleſs, tho' the gains had been but little by the bargain. But as he was neither witty nor handſom enough for the Conqueſt, 'twas in vain ſhe encouraged him to it, for he ſcarcely attempted it, tho' the Mareſchal who had forbid her the ſight of his Wife, had not laid the ſame injunction upon the Husband, which afforded him an opportunity of ſeeing her continually. The Counteſs (who knew what her Husband did, by the means of <hi>Beuvron,</hi> who had found the ſecret to be as well receiv'd by him as by his Wife) find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:42116:46"/> how little the affair was advanc'd, ſaw ſhe was forc'd once more to change the battery, and after ſhe had contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plated upon ſeveral ways and deſigns, ſhe at laſt had the good Fortune to fall upon one which ſhe concluded would anſwer the intent. She had obſerv'd whilſt ſhe viſited her Siſter, that there was a <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> who belong'd to her, perfectly well made, and who was not inſenſible of it, ſo that believing if ſhe could inſpire him with a deſign to make love to his Miſtreſs, to which his Age, and the opportunity would ſoon make him condeſcend, it might prove a ſucceſsful Expedient to ſignalize her revenge.</p>
                  <p>Ruminating upon this Affair, one morning ſhe ſent for the <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> and was very much pleas'd with his Wit, which was a neceſſary inſtrument in the forwarding this deſign. But what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted her more, was, that the Boy, born of an honeſt Family, and forc'd by neceſſity to this Employment, would give her no account of his Birth; upon which ſhe grounded a cunning Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, that ſerv'd her not a little upon this occaſion. For ſhe inſinuated into her Siſter, by the means of the Marqueſs
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:42116:46"/> 
                     <hi>de Beuvron,</hi> that he was certainly ſome perſon of Quality, who being very much in love with her, had ſor that reaſon condeſcended to this diſguiſe. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalleſs, who had not yet perhaps ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of his good Meen, look'd upon him after this with more attention; and ſinding him perfectly handſom, ſhe ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily believing what ſhe deſir'd, ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd this Fable for truth. To be more aſſur'd of it, ſhe often ask'd him about his Country and Birth, but the ſame reaſons which oblig'd him to conceal 'em from Madam <hi>d'Olonne</hi> continuing ſtill, he was as reſerv'd to her, and ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd his ſilence to his advantage.</p>
                  <p>The Marqueſs <hi>de Beuvron,</hi> who viſited her for no other reaſon but to diſcover her mind, found her very reſerv'd upon that point, for ſhe had conſider'd ſhe was oblig'd to put him off, ſhould ſhe ſeem to be perſwaded that he was a man of Quality; So ſhe turn'd it into raillery, but ſhe had to deal with a cunning <hi>Normand,</hi> who ſaw through the Vail notwithſtanding all her Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſice, and return'd to tell the Counteſs ſhe had knock'd the nail on the head. This diſcovery made the Counteſs ſend for the Boy a ſecond time, acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:42116:47"/> him, that ſhe had perceiv'd her Siſter did not hate him, but bid him for his Lifes ſake, take ſuch care of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, that no body might obſerve it; telling him, that ſhe did not deſire him to deſiſt, ſince (if his Miſtreſs's temper inclin'd her to Love) ſhe might as well beſtow the favour upon him, as on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, whereby the Intrigue might make a greater noiſe in the World. That he ſhould be ſure to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with all reſpect to her, and above all things take care not to undeceive her Siſter, in the opinion ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd of his being of a much better condition than he appear'd.</p>
                  <p>Tho' the Boy was aſtoniſh'd at the beginning of this Diſcourſe, he grew more aſſur'd at the end, and the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions the Mareſchalleſs often ask'd him, making him preſume what he heard was true, he gave himſelf over to thoughts of Vanity, which were not inexcuſable in him. What they had told him ſeem'd no little happineſs to him. For not conſidering the Quality of his Miſtreſs, ſhe was extreamly Charming, tho' in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently handſom; ſo that there were a thouſand ſiner Women, who yet were nothing ſo agreeable. To make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42116:47"/> more amiable, he dreſs'd himſelf as clean and decently as he could; which together with the diligence he ſhew'd towards her, made the Mareſ hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſoon believe that all ſhe thought of him was true. In ſine, the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity he had to ſee her dreſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs her ſelf, in which ſhe more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly employ'd him than others, made him fall ſo deeply in love with her, that it was eaſie to perceive, that Love is not always the Effect of Deſtiny.</p>
                  <p>The Mareſchalleſs was ſenſible thoſe aſſiduous Services he render'd her, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a more noble cauſe than that which generally influences Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. And as ſhe confirm'd her ſelf more every day in the Opinion ſhe had conceiv'd that he was not of an obſcure Birth, ſhe was not ungrateful to the ſecret teſtimonies he gave her of his Paſſion. But yet that ſhe might have nothing to reproach her ſelf withal, forc'd him almoſt to tell her that he was a man of Quality; ſo that he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was no other Obſtacle but this to his good Fortune, aſſum'd the name of a good Family in his Country, which the Mareſchalleſs, ſince ſhe ſo much deſir'd it, eaſily believ'd. He was not
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:42116:48"/> at all deceiv'd in the thoughts he had, that this would advance his Aſſairs. The Lady who thought it no diſgrace to love ſo handſom a Youth, made ſuch returns to his Paſſion, that it was diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to determine on which part were the moſt violent inclinations, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs for want of Confidence, he made her languiſh yet two Months in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of what ſhe moſt deſir'd; when that ſhe might no longer be tortur'd with deſire, ſhe reſolv'd to make him ſuch advances, that it ſhould be impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to doubt any longer of the Joys he was invited to.</p>
                  <p>She had obſerv'd that he had a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Love for Hair, and deſirous to raiſe his paſſion to the higheſt pitch, ſhe had often ſuffer'd him to comb her head, tho' much to her coſt, he being not very dextrous at it; the fire ſhe perceiv'd ſparkling in his Eyes, made her not complain of the inconvenience ſhe endur'd by it, thinking that this would ſtill encourage him. One morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when ſhe was at her Toillette, ſhe ſent for him, pretending ſhe had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for him to write ſome Letters. When he came, ſhe bid her Servants retire, ſince ſhe had ſome ſecret mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:42116:48"/> to dictate to him; but preſenting the Combs to him inſtead of a Pen, and ſaying many obliging things, he was pleas'd, and became as red as fire. This had been enough for one that had known the World, but he, who was afraid of being guilty of any diſreſpect that might occaſion his diſcharge, had ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſo dull not to have profited by the opportunity, had not the Lady, who kindly interpreted his proceedings, forc'd him into her lap, where ſhe made him ſo many advances, that he could no longer be in doubt of his good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. At theſe ſigns he took Courage, and the Bed being not yet made, the half hour he remain'd with her, was ſo well employ'd, that ſhe conceiv'd a great eſteem of his merit. She wiſh'd that ſhe might have yet enjoy'd an hour or two's entertainment with him, but being oblig'd to ſome meaſures, leſt her Servants might ſuſpect her, ſhe made him ſold up ſome ſheets of paper as if they had been Letters, and recovering her ſelf from the diſorders which are inevitable in theſe Rencounters, ſhe call'd for a Candle to ſeal the Letters.</p>
                  <p>This Intrigue was not ſuſpected by any one, and if the Reſentment which
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42116:49"/> the Counteſs <hi>d'Olonne</hi> had conceiv'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Mareſchal, would have given her leave to have been leſs miſchievous, it might have long remain'd undiſcover'd. But her deſign being to torment him, ſhe had ſo narrowly obſerv'd 'em, that ſhe queſtion'd not the ſucceſs of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances. She was every day confirm'd in this opinion by the different advice ſhe had from the Spys ſhe had engag'd to that purpoſe, and believing it now as an Article of Faith, ſhe no ſooner underſtood that the Mareſchal was to return from the Army, when ſhe made uſe of an unknown hand to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with this diſagreeable news. He receiv'd the Letter upon his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſinding no name to it, and the Character unknown to him, he at firſt imagin'd it for a Jeſt put upon him. Nevertheleſs being of a jealous nature, he reſolv'd to benefit by the Advice, and to obſerve both their Conducts ſo exactly, that it ſhould be impoſſible for any thing to paſs undiſcern'd.</p>
                  <p>With theſe thoughts he arriv'd at <hi>Paris,</hi> and diſſimulation being neceſſary, he us'd his Wife with ſo much tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that it was impoſſible to divine his intentions, thinking him ſo far from
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42116:49"/> ſuſpicion, ſhs us'd no conſtraint to her Favourite, but treated him with the ſame freedom, as in the Mareſchals ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
                  <p>The poor Cuckold ſoon perceiv'd the Intrigue, and was more politick then could be imagin'd, for tho' he was brutality it ſelf, as I have before ſaid, he took the readieſt courſe to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his revenge by ſhewing no miſtruſt of it, which ſo far deceiv'd his Wife, that there often paſs'd thoſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, which made him not queſtion his being of the Brotherhood. His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment was not the leſs for being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, on the contrary, it diſturb'd his quiet both Night and Day; which afforded no little joy to the Counteſs, <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> who was ſo clear ſighted to diſcern through all his falſe diſguiſes, he ſuffer'd all the torture ſhe could wiſh him. For ſhe not only knew that he retain'd people to watch the Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, but had alſo bargain'd with 'em to aſſaſſinate the <hi>Valet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was indeed his firſt deſign, but reflecting that ſuch kind of people, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to many accidents, might one day accuſe him, broke it off to follow juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er meaſures. The Counteſs <hi>d'Olonne</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:42116:50"/> who diſcover'd every day more of his diſcontent and inquſetude, could not forbear triumphing at it, which ſhews that a Woman may be at the ſame time engag'd in two violent Paſſions, for both the deſire of revenge, and the care of making Love, were to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in her of an equal degree.</p>
                  <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>Beuvron,</hi> was ſtill her Gallant, but being forc'd to ſhare his good Fortune amongſt many of all forts of Conditions, he grew concern'd at it; and to revenge himſelf, acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Mareſchalleſs with the trick her Siſter had play'd her. It is eaſie to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, what anger and trouble was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindled at this news, and you may judge of it by her reſolutions: for tho' her paſſion for her Favourite was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, as well as her inclinations to debauchery, being more concern'd for her Life, ſhe broke off all Commerce with him, and would have him be gone out of the Houſe. Several hints had preceded ſo ſurpriſing a Declaration, that he might eſteem the thing leſs grievous. And ſhe alſo told him of the notice ſhe had receiv'd, to ſhew him that nothing but neceſſity could oblige her to it; but whether he took all this
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42116:50"/> for pretence, or whether his Deſtiny drew him to the Precipice from which he ſoon after fell, he deſir'd eight days time to reſolve in; which ſhe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to refuſe, he had in that time diſcover'd he was to be turn'd away, which coming to the Mareſchal's Ears, he receiv'd him from his Wife's, into his own Service, leſt his retreat ſhould free him from the revenge he was me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating againſt him.</p>
                  <p>The hopes that the <hi>Valet</hi> had that his preſence might revive thoſe Flames that had been ſo agreeable to him, made him accept the offer, without acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mareſchalleſs; when ſhe knew of it, ſhe was ready to dye with grief, for ſhe thought, when he was gone, ſhe ſhould ſoon forget what was paſs'd, and that her Husband not knowing the depth of the Intrigue, would by degrees be free'd from the jealouſie he had conceiv'd. The Mareſchal, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his revenge look'd kinder upon this new Comer than on his ancient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and employing him before the others, incenſibly drew him to that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice that was his deſtruction; For taking a Journey not long after this, towards his Government of <hi>Lorain,</hi> he
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42116:51"/> by the way Aſſaſſinated him with his own hand, that no one might know what was become of him, it happen'd after this manner. He pretended to have made a ſmall Love Intrigue, and went thither two or three times, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany'd only with this <hi>Valet,</hi> which had ſpread ſuch a Jealouſie amongſt the reſt of the Servants, that they thought he alone had now the benefit of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Ear. But as he was travelling one day, he bid him alight to mend ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing about his Stirrup, and ſiring a Piſtol at his head, the Fellow dropt down dead upon the place. When he had perform'd this noble Action, he went to <hi>Nancy,</hi> where counterfeiting a trouble to know what was become of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, whom he pretended to have ſent on ſome buſineſs, the Fate of the poor Wretch was at length diſcover'd to him by ſome wandring Parties. The Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Luxenburgh,</hi> having at this time ſent Parties abroad, this Murder was attributed to them, and the Mareſchal ſeem'd to be ſo incens'd at it, that he commanded a Village in that Dutchy to be burnt, tho' it was then under Contribution.</p>
                  <p>As there was not any perſon who
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:42116:51"/> knew any reaſon he had to be diſpleas'd with this Servant, ſo they could not lay this ill Action to his Charge; and even his Wife believ'd that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports concerning his Death were true; ſhe had almoſt forgot him ſince his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, ſo that ſhe was not very much afflicted to be thus rid of him. Yet her joy for it laſted not long, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Beuvron,</hi> who was as I have ſaid, a cunning <hi>Normand,</hi> having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly inform'd himſelf of all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in this murder, found out the truth, and told Madam <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> with whom he was reconcil'd, that her Siſter was in no little danger, and they ſhould do well to advertiſe her of it. When Madam <hi>d'Olonne</hi> had reflected upon the thing, ſhe made no doubt but he was in the right, charging him to inform her of it immediately; he went and found her dreſs'd, for imagining ſhe had nothing now to fear, ſhe thought of nothing but engaging a freſh Lover.</p>
                  <p>The Marqueſs, fraught with this ill news, had ſet his face in the form he thought moſt ſuitable to this melancholy tale, which the Mareſchalleſs obſerving, told him with a gay air, now indeed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42116:52"/> ſhe found he was in Love, for it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly appear'd in his face. That may be, Madam, <hi>replyed Beuvron,</hi> and who can defend themſelves from it; but let me aſſure you that what appears there now, proceeds not from that cauſe, but is rather an effect of Friendſhip, for altho' it is not very Courtly for me to tell you I am not in Love with you, yet nevertheleſs upon my Word, I am not leſs diſquieted for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you. Hereupon he told her what had paſs'd in the Army; which the Mareſchalleſs contradicting, boy'd up by her thoughts that things were in a better ſrame, he quickly ſo unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd her, that ſhe was thrown into a very uneaſie concern, had ſhe known that all this miſchief proceeded from her Siſter, ſhe would never have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given her, but far from the thoughts of it, ſhe told <hi>Beuvron</hi> that ſhe knew not what to do in this extremity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring his advice, whom ſhe imagin'd, ſince he had ſome intereſt in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, would be glad to oblige her.</p>
                  <p>'Twas eaſier to make theſe Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon this occaſion, than to give ſound advice, yet <hi>Bevron,</hi> to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Man of Parts, propos'd ſeveral
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:42116:52"/> things to her, and ſhe ſix'd upon one which was to be of ſo reſerv'd a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in her Husbands abſence, that what opinion ſoever he had of her, he could not but believe ſhe had now a deſign to change her courſe of life; this oblig'd her to diſperſe a company of young people drawn thither and increas'd by a gay freedom which coſt her much pains to be rid off. Some few of the leſt dangerous only continued, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt 'em the Count <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> who encouraged by his Wife, as I have ſaid before, was grown ſo much in love, that he reſted neither day nor night.</p>
                  <p>The private Converſations that the Marqueſs <hi>de Beuvron</hi> had with her, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering ſome Beauties to him, which he had not obſerv'd whilſt he was in love with her Siſter; he began now to ſee her rather out of Inclination than neceſſity, and as his experience in the World had taught him that ſo much time was loſt, as was ſpent with a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy without acquainting her with his Sentiments. Madam, <hi>ſays he one day,</hi> I have hitherto endeavoured to render you ſervice without hopes of a return, and the reaſon of it was, that not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the honour to ſee you often, I
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42116:53"/> had only a ſlight knowledge of your merit, but ſince I have had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to converſe with you frequently, it had given me an opportunity to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern ſome Excellencies, that are rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be met withal, and I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to you, I ſhould be guilty of a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, ſhould I ſay I did not love you: I know, Madam, you will tell me that I love Madam <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> that is true, or to ſpeak more properly, was true heretofore, but the time is now paſs'd, neither am I to be branded with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy; ſhe has given me reaſon enough to diſengage my ſelf by her unfaithfulneſs, not to mention how lawful an Excuſe, a perſon like you is, for any alteration of Paſſion.</p>
                  <p>This Compliment was not diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Lady, tho' the maker of it had but ſome few days before, given her advice very contrary to it. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the pleaſure a Woman always takes to hear you are in love with her, ſhe had a ſecret envy to her Siſter, who had mean thoughts of her beauty; ſo that ſhe could not more convince her, how much ſhe was miſtaken in her opinion, than by robbing her of one who had long lov'd her, and ſerv'd her as a ſecond Husband.</p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:42116:53"/>
                  <p>Theſe Reaſons, with ſome others which I ſhall not mention, made her return as ſoft an anſwer to <hi>Beuvron</hi> as he could wiſh, for, without ſo much as ſeeming not to believe what he ſaid, ſhe only mention'd the difficulty he would have to forget her Siſter, and the fear ſhe ſtood in of her Husband. To one part he anſwered her, that the Mareſchal would be leſs jealous of him than any, ſince, believing him (with the reſt of the World) ſo extreamly inamour'd with Madam <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> if the report of it ſhould come to his Ears, he would be the laſt that could believe it; and for the other, ſhe muſt take him either for a Man of a very low Spirit, or a blind dotard, that after ſo remarkable a Conduct as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs's, his Paſſion ſhould continue for her; that he was by Nature Conſtant, but not inſenſible; that to confeſs the truth, 'twas indignation began the diſengage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the Paſſion he had for her that perfected it; that truly her fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were not ſo regular as her Siſters, but the leaſt of her Charms and good Qualities gave her much the advantage of her.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:42116:54"/>
                  <p>This was a great deal to be believ'd; for the Counteſs was without diſpute one of the fineſt Women in <hi>France.</hi> But <hi>Beuvron</hi> accompanying his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with ſome Actions which prov'd he was truely concern'd, it was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to perſwade the Lady, who, as I have already ſaid, had a good opinion of her ſelf, that he was very much in love, ſo that not wanting deſire, and he ſeeming to her handſom enough to take the <hi>Valet de Chambre</hi>'s place, ſhe made no other pretenſes to ſhew ſhe doubted of his Diſcourſe: But on the contrary, told him what obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhe had to him for his good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that if ſhe ſhould happen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend too eaſily, he might attribute it to her acknowledgement. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Beuvron,</hi> who knew how to live, very well underſtood the meaning of this, and not ſuffering the Diſcourſe to range any farther, with fury ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at the greateſt Bliſs.</p>
                  <p>The Lady found him a good actor in the Comedy they had been playing together, which his Barbary ſhape and looſe air, could not make her believe. But his Hair which was black, ſuppl'y'd the defects, and the Lady appear'd to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42116:54"/> him ſo engageing, that he could not but perform ſomething extraordinary for her ſervice. She ask'd him which (meaning ſhe or her Siſter,) afforded him the moſt raviſhing tranſports, and and the Intrigue being ſo publick, that every body knew of it, he thought it would be diſobliging to deny it, and laying aſide his diſcretion, freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, her ſelf without Compariſon: She ſeem'd not to believe him, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Raptures did not appear to her violent enough, but this was only to give him the opportunity to begin again; which he perceiving, acquitted himſelf ſo well of his Duty, that ſhe was forc'd to confeſs that if he did not love her, his treatment to her had very much the appearances of it.</p>
                  <p>This enterview being paſs'd in this manner, we may eaſily imagine they parted good Friends, and with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to ſee each other at the firſt opportunity; in fine, they had ſeveral Meetings without the leaſt ſuſpicion of harm, ſo unalterably fix'd to her Siſter was he generally imagin'd, but yet the Count <hi>d'Olonne</hi> was not deceiv'd, which was a wonder, ſince he was reputed no great Conjurer. This poor Cuckold
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:42116:55"/> not to be the only one without a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, had endeavoured to gain the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalleſs's favour, and as the Jealous have Eyes that ſee through all things. he, who did not ſo much as miſtruſt his Wife's deportment, was ſo aſſur'd of the falſeneſs of his Miſtreſs, that he was reſolv'd to quarrel with <hi>Beuvron</hi> about it. Who could have believ'd him of ſuch dangerous Reſolutions, who us'd to entertain as a maxim, that he who drew his Sword, ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by the Sword? neither would he ever engage in the perillous trade of War; and tho' his Father had bought him a conſiderable Employment, he being oblig'd by it on ſome occaſions to get on Horſeback for the King's Service, he ſoon thought fit to part with it. Neither was his Rival much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like him in his temper, for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he had procur'd an Employment, that was not more dangerous in War than peace, each being of the beſt Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in <hi>France,</hi> which had heretofore produc'd conſiderable Hero's.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>D'Olonne</hi> therefore knowing that he had to do with one that was not more miſchievous than himſelf, was the more willing to quarrel with him, and in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:42116:55"/> ſo furious a manner, that nothing leſs than cutting of throats was expected, in effect there was enough paſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, to have occaſion'd unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable feuds in others; but the noiſe of their quarrel being ſpread all over <hi>Paris,</hi> their Friends endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile 'em, but could never ſucceed; they ſtill grew the more violent, which the peace-makers perceiving, left them at liberty, not apprehending any great danger was likely to enſue. Neither were they deceiv'd, for when they found the Bridle was on their necks, they began to think they were in the wrong, not to take their Friends advice, which made it not difficult for Madam <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> who was afraid of loſing <hi>Beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vron,</hi> to Counſel her Husband not to venture himſelf ſo raſhly; ſo that without entring into particulars, ſhe made 'em promiſe to be Friends. To this purpoſe, ſhe ſaid, ſhe would treat 'em both with a Supper in her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>d'Olonne</hi> conſented to it, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in her preſence he might caſt ſome reflections upon <hi>Beuvron,</hi> whom he thought was too aſſiduous with her, and he muſt have been ſtark blind not to perceive there was a great inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy betwixt 'em.</p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:42116:56"/>
                  <p>Thoſe who knew of their quarrel, imagin'd ſhe was the occaſion of it, but when they found her the Mareſchal of <hi>France,</hi> that is the reconciler, they knew not what to think. <hi>Beuvron</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Rendezvous, <hi>d'Olonne</hi> told his Wife the whole truth of the Quarrel, pretending he could not ſee him at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the diſhonour of his Siſter and not reſent it; this I'll aſſure you was no ſwall Stratagem for him, who was reported to be guilty of but few in his own affairs; but yet it availed nothing with her, for ſhe imagin'd, as it was true, that he was in Love himſelf with her Siſter, and that Jealouſie only had the power to draw him to this violence. This anſwer'd not the intent of the Huſband, who would have had her quarrell'd with <hi>Beuvron</hi> for his inſideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and for that reaſon had conſented to the accommodation; ſhe was as jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as another, but ſhe believ'd her Husband had taken a falſe allarm; and what confirm'd her in this Opinion was, that ſhe had her ſelf commanded <hi>Beuvron</hi> to ſee her Siſter privately, which ſhe thought the occaſion of all this diſorder.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:42116:56"/>
                  <p>This happen'd whilſt the King was young, and but little of his adroitneſs either in War or Love had yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd; but as he had the inclinations of a great Prince, of all the Women about Court theſe two Siſters were the leaſt in his eſteem, and he could not forbear to ſay one day, ſpeaking of the Counteſs <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> that ſhe was a ſhame to her Sex, and that her Siſter was going the way to be little better. In effect finding her Husband more tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable at his return that ſhe could hope, ſhe ſtopped not at the Marqueſs <hi>de Beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vron,</hi> but aſſociated with him many Comrades of all ſorts. The Church, the Law, and the Sword, was equally well receiv'd by her, and not content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with theſe three States, ſhe made a Favourite of a fourth. Thoſe who were concern'd in the Revenue pleas'd her extreamly, and having a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for Play, many believ'd her Intereſt engag'd her to it.</p>
                  <p>The Marqueſs <hi>de Beuvron</hi> believing himſelf handſom enough to be happy, was not contented with the leavings of ſo many; and Madam <hi>d'Olonne</hi> being not more faithful to him, he not only reſolved to ſee neither of 'em, but
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42116:57"/> alſo to ruin their Reputations in the World. As he durſt not brag pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly to have lain with two Siſters, he gave 'cm to underſtand he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd that happineſs with one, and that it was only his own fault that he had not arriv'd to it with the other. Thoſe who knew 'em both, had no hardſhip to believe it, but many believing it was malice that occaſion'd his railing, the injury he thought to do their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, excited only in them a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity to ſee ſuch remarkable Ladies.</p>
                  <p>It was no wonder that the Count <hi>d'Olonne</hi> ſhould be ſo accuſtom'd to his Wifes receiving Viſits, ſince his Houſe had never ſince his marriage been free from people of all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But that the Mareſchal <hi>de la Ferté</hi> ſhould ſuffer it, was not to be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; eſpecially when he had made her ſo Cavalier a Complement the day after his Wedding, and upon a bare ſuſpicion had himſelf aſſaſſinated his <hi>Valet de Chambre.</hi> 'Tis ſtrange that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe actions he ſhould ever pardon her, but it was for a Reaſon not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally known, and which I am going to relate. The Mareſchal, as brutal as he was, fell ſometimes in Love, and the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42116:57"/> Marqueſs <hi>de Beuvron,</hi> whoſe Intrigue then continu'd, had, to put him in good Humour at his return from <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> taken as pretty a Girl as any in <hi>Paris,</hi> out of a publick Houſe, and plac'd her here, that ſhe might pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually perform what he deſired. The Mareſchal was no ſooner returned, but he began to be taken with her, ſhe was ſo handſom, and of ſo good a ſhape, that it was not ſtrange he ſhould fall into her Nets. He look'd very much upon her, and believing her as vertuous as ſhe affected to appear, it was not long before he made her an offer of his Heart. She at firſt refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, and his paſſion was ſo enſlam'd by the denyal, that he openly Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her. his Wife to puſh on the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, pretended to be offended at it, but he deſiſted not for this, neither car'd ſhe much, for what ſhe did, was only to make him believe he was not indifferent to her.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Veſtal</hi> had perform'd all the little tricks ſhe thought neceſſary to force him into the better opinion of her Perſon, ſhe yielded to his deſires; and tho' the Mareſchal's fortune in it was not extraordinary, he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:42116:58"/> ſo charm'd with it, that he could no longer live without her. She performed her duty towards him very well, by following the orders were given her: And ſhe took great care to entertain him with the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Mareſchalleſs, under the pretext that having a Wife ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in all things, the Paſſion he had for her would no doubt be quickly expir'd. It was not the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalleſs or <hi>Beuvron</hi>'s deſign that ſhe ſhould proceed as far, for they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, recommended to her to be prudent; but they found they were miſtaken, when they relyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a one as ſhe was, and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid leſt, inſtead of the Service they thought to reap by it, (ſhe having gone beyond their Commands) their affairs might be rendered worſe, by diſcoveting the ſecret, to prevent the worſt, he caus'd her one day to be taken away by ſtealth, and carry'd her to <hi>Rouen,</hi> from whence he ſent her to <hi>America.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Mareſchal made a great noiſe about it, and attributed it to his Wife's Jealouſie, which ſhe did not at all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. This occaſion'd a breach for ſome
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:42116:58"/> time, but the Mareſchal's love fit being over, he was reconcil'd to her, and the Friendſhip he ſhew'd her, was ſo much the more ſincere, as he believ'd a Woman capable of ſo much jealouſie, could by no means be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful to him. By this means ſhe regain'd his Confidence in her, which made the Town, not ſo eaſie to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd as the Mareſchal, conclude that it is in a Womans power to tame the moſt ſavage Beaſt. In fine, he ſuffer'd her not only to ſee all ſorts of Company under the pretence of Play, which ſhe introduc'd at home; but alſo furniſh'd her with all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney he could procure, whilſt his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors at <hi>Paris</hi> were clamouring after him for the money he ow'd 'em.</p>
                  <p>At this permiſſion to ſee Company her heart was overjoy'd. All the youth of the Court paſs'd through her hands, whilſt the Counteſs <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> old, and deſpis'd, was forc'd to retrench her ſelf to <hi>Feruaques,</hi> who had no other good qualities but that of being rich, and of the ſame name with one who had been a Mareſchal of <hi>France.</hi> He was of a good Family on his Mothers ſide, but very mean on his Fathers;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42116:59"/> ſo that ſhe us'd him ſo ſcurvily, as if the refuſe of the whole World had been too good for him; and ſeeming to be aſhamed of the Amour, ſhe who had never taken any meaſures in debauchery, made it be publickly reported that ſhe ſaw him for no other reaſon, but to endeavour to marry him to her Niece, Mademoiſelle <hi>de la Ferté,</hi> who was not very rich, and would by this means have her neceſſity ſupply'd, and to blind the people more, ſhe made him buy the Government of the Province <hi>du Main,</hi> declaring it was for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than that her Niece might have a Husband of ſome rank. But being quickly tir'd with theſe Contrivances, they took lodgings together, and his Relations were afraid, leſt he ſhould be guilty of the Folly to marry her, in caſe her Husband ſhould dye. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Bonelle,</hi> his Mother, was moſt allarm'd at it, proteſting, that ſhe ſhould never be at quiet if this ſhould happen. This was told again to Madam <hi>d'O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonne,</hi> who not conſidering <hi>Feruaques's</hi> innocence, let her reſentment fall upon him. She ask'd him if he was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe falſe reports, and if he was vain enough to believe that ſhe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:42116:59"/> would marry him, ſhould ſhe be a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. <hi>Feruaques</hi> was concern'd at this ſlight, and returning an anſwer which did not pleaſe her, ſhe took the Tongs and pinch'd him by the face; he pay'd her ſo much reſpect, that he only ask'd her what ſhe was doing, and whether ſhe had well conſidered of it? So Sottiſh a queſtion deſerv'd a freſh pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, ſo that believing him a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Fool than before, ſhe continu'd to uſe him ſo ill, that he was much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figur'd, and durſt not ſtir out for eight days.</p>
                  <p>Madam de <hi>Bonnelle</hi> being acquainted (by what means I know not) with this Adventure, was ready to run mad; and had ſhe brought the Eſtate, ſhe would have certainly given it all to her other Son <hi>Bullion.</hi> But nevertheleſs ſhe thought it neceſſary to remind <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruaques</hi> of his Honour, and having not ſeem him ſince he lodg'd with her, ſhe ſent her Woman to ſpeak with him. Madam <hi>d'Olonne</hi> was by chance going forth as ſhe came in, and Madam <hi>de Bonelle</hi> bidding her Servant take no notice of her, in caſe ſhe ſhould meet her, ſhe fairly paſs'd on without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any obeyſance. The Counteſs
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:42116:60"/> 
                     <hi>d'Olonne</hi> knew her, and not queſtioning but what ſhe did was by Command; 'tis thus ſays ſhe aloud, that ill bred people inſtruct their Sevants, and if I did my ſelf Juſtice, I ſhould have you corrected for it. The Woman heard plainly what ſhe ſaid, and being not aſſur'd but ſhe might be as good as her Word, ſhe was ſorry ſhe had ſo punctually executed her Miſtreſſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. But the Lady going on after theſe Words, ſhe continu'd her way al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and acquitted her ſelf of her Meſſage. She found <hi>Feruaques</hi> with his head bound his face black and blue, and one of his Eyes almoſt put out; and being an antient Servant, who us'd to ſpeak freely to him, are you not aſham'd? ſays ſhe, and can you think of the condition you are in, without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? He would have diſſembled the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but when the Woman ſaid the whole ſtory was ſufficiently known, he was very much confus'd at it, but yet he would not conſent to what ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, which was to leave Madam <hi>d'O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonne,</hi> and oblige his Mother who was dying with grief at it.</p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:42116:60"/>
                  <p>'Twas not ill Fortune to an Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lady, as the Counteſs was, to have the enjoyment of a Lover young and rich, but yet ſhe fell far ſhort of her Siſter, who after ſhe had taſted of all the Court, and even her Brother in Law, was ſo lucky to engage a young Prince of great Merit, the Duke of <hi>Longueville,</hi> Nephew to the Prince of <hi>Condée.</hi> He was not yet twenty, but being very handſom, and of a ſhape that promiſed great pleaſures; there was no Woman about Court, who had not made ſome attempt upon his Heart. The Mareſchalleſs, who if I may ſay ſo, was continually beating up Volunteers for Love, queſtioning her Reputation, and therefore doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of her happineſs, was ſecretly ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee ſo noble a Conqueſt ſcape her. <hi>De Fieſque</hi> was her Friend, tho' not of that kind that had aſpir'd to enjoy her, ſo that ſhe imagin'd ſhe might freely open her heart to him, and not occaſion Jealouſie. 'Tis a ſtrange thing, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> that I hear ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of the Duke of <hi>Longueville,</hi> and that I have no acquaintance with him. He viſits every body but me, and ſome Women are much happier then
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:42116:61"/> others; I know a thouſand that he goes to ſee, who without vanity, are no better than my ſelf, and to tell you the truth, my dear Count, it torments me to ſee him in their Company, either at the <hi>Thuilleries,</hi> or other publick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, whilſt I have only the civility of a Hat. <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> who was complaiſance it ſelf, told her ſhe had reaſon and ought to be much concern'd at it, and when he had told her ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things in advantage of her Beauty, and Wit, to perſwade her ſhe had a right to pretend to this Conqueſt. What would you have me ſay, continued he, ſometimes your conduct is irregular, and if I may ſpeak ſincerely, every one is not of your humour. The Duke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives me as his Friend, and as one of his moſt intimate, ſo that he has been ſo free as to diſcover his Heart to me, and was I not afraid that it would be diſagreeable to you, I would tell you what he ſays of you. At theſe words the Mareſchalleſs bluſh'd, but being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous that this Intrigue ſhould be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a happy concluſion; ſhe would bear with ſome ungrateful truths, in hopes they might be uſeful to her. She therefore conjur'd him to conceal
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:42116:61"/> nothing from her, ſaying, ſhe would be ſo far from taking it ill, that ſhe was angry with him for not diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it to her ſooner, and that that reſerve was an Argument he was not ſo good a Friend as ſhe had always eſteem'd him, but if he did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly repair the Fault, ſhe would never forgive him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>De Fieſque</hi> finding by her concern, that it would oblige her to ſpeak free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, told her that the Duke thought it not well that ſhe receiv'd ſo much Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: That he had ſeveral times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd to him, that he found her hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, neither could ſhe be more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his Eye, but ſo great a reſort to her was intollerable; neither could he believe ſhe lov'd the Count <hi>d'Olonne</hi> as was reported, without extreamly leſſening the eſteem he had for her; ſaying amongſt other things, that to love ſo ridiculous a Man as the Count, muſt be a Sign of perfect debauchery. That if ſhe had any deſign upon the Duke, ſhe muſt begin it with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of her Conduct. That to do her ſervice, he would be ſure to let him know it was for his ſake, ſo that the ill Impreſſions he had of her wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42116:62"/> off by degrees, his Eſteem for her would encreaſe, which would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly produce all ſhe could wiſh or hope.</p>
                  <p>The Duke had taken ſuch poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her heart, that ſhe could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the offer. She thank'd <hi>de Fieſque</hi> for his good advice, and, not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to find how much of what he ſaid was Complement, ſhe ſeem'd perſwaded of the truth, and was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uneaſie to know, if in caſe ſhe ſhould refuſe all Company, it would give a ſatisfaction to his Friend. The Count told her ſhe had no reaſon to doubt of it, and that he for his part would take care to perſwade him, that a Woman who was capable of doing, without an acquaintance, ſo much for his ſake, would perform any thing when he ſhould return an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>'Twas thus that the Mareſchalleſs, by the neceſſities of her temper, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd the Laws of Nature; for, not conſidering that 'twas the Woman's part to expect the Courtſhip from the Man, it is evident, that ſhe firſt made Love to the Duke of <hi>Longueville.</hi> The Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> who believ'd ſhe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:42116:62"/> would find it very difficult to diſcharge ſo many favourites for the ſake and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of one, mention'd nothing at firſt, of this Converſation to the Duke; but when he found ſhe began in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to effect her Promiſe, and had parted with the Count <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> the Marqueſs <hi>Deffiat,</hi> and many more too tedious to name; he thought himſelf oblig'd to perform his promiſe. The Duke <hi>de Longueville,</hi> when he had known what paſs'd, was glad ſhe had taken this Courſe, for it would have otherwiſe been impoſſible for him to love her; that now ſince all obſtacles were remov'd, he conſented to viſit her, deſiring him to acquaint her he would come to ſee her in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and that he ſhould be a witneſs of their firſt Converſation. The Count did what he could to excuſe himſelf, telling him that a third perſon made but an ill figure at ſuch interviews, but the Duke deſiring it for ſeveral reaſons; firſt, becauſe he would have one who was a Friend to both preſent, to witneſs upon what conditions they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and in the ſecond place, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a condition to perform the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes he might make, he ſhould be ſure
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:42116:63"/> of an Excuſe to defer the Payment to a more favourable opportunity.</p>
                  <p>In ſine, too much health had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned his ſickneſs, for frequenting too often ſome brisk Ladies about Court, he was forc'd to retire from theirs, to put himſelf into the Chirurgeons hands. <hi>De Fieſque</hi> ſeeing he would have it ſo, was oblig'd to condeſcend, and having acquainted the Lady of the viſit, ſhe dreſs'd her ſelf extraordinary fine to receive him. But the Duke on the contrary, was in a courſe Suit of gray Cloth, tho' he did not appear the leſs Charming to the Lady for his negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. So that eager to content her deſires, ſhe was ſorry he had brought the Count <hi>de Fieſque</hi> with him, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by it leſt his expectations were not ſo paſſionate as hers. The Duke after the firſt Compliments, told her that having heard from his Friend how much he was oblig'd to her, he came not only to return her thanks, but to Vow an eternal Friendſhip for her. That it ſhould be her fault, if they did not love as long as they liv'd, and 'twas for that reaſon he had brought the Count, that he might reproach him with his falſeneſs, if he ſhould
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:42116:63"/> ever be worſe than his engagement. That he would never ſee Mademoiſelle <hi>de Fienne</hi> any more, to whom he was thought a Friend, but would leave her to the Chevalier <hi>de Lorain,</hi> her rightful Patron, and would perform the ſame to all the reſt of the Ladies that were ſuſpected, and ſhe had only to advertiſe him if there was any one ſhe would not have him ſee. But he requir'd, that ſhe ſhould for her part, promiſe the ſame thing concerning thoſe he ſhould be jealous of; adding that he was ſo critical, that it was impoſſible for him to perceive any thing of that nature, and not have a quarrel with her for ever about it.</p>
                  <p>The Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> who was a mediator on this occaſion, ſaid, that it was too reaſonable, and the Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs too juſt to oppoſe it. And in effect, ſhe was ſo far from contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, that with the greateſt ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhe ſeem'd to wiſh all miſchief might happen unto her, if ſhe would not do any thing for the poſſeſſion of ſo illuſtrious a heart. The bargain thus concluded, without more Ceremony, he kiſs'd her hand, in token of the Friendſhip he had vow'd to her; when
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:42116:64"/> ſhe, who thought thoſe earneſts not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, threw her arms about his neck, and gave him a thouſand amorous kiſſes: Had not the Prince been indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, his temper had been too acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging to have omitted a ſuitable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. But knowing that it was not in this Diſtemper, that a hair of the ſame Dog was to be taken for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; he broke off the entertainment as ſoon as he could, upon promiſe to return alone the next day. But as it was impoſſible for him to make his Court in the right method, without occaſioning both their Repentance, he pretended to be ſick, which afforded him time to prepare for the Combat ſhe expected.</p>
                  <p>The Viſit he made her allarm'd the diſcarded Lovers, and not any of 'em doubted but it was to him they were ſacrific'd. Yet no other following of ſome time, it a little amus'd 'em, I mean upon his account, for having the ſame ill treatment continued to them, they were not the leſs unhappy; for their jealouſie, changing only the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, furniſh'd 'em with reaſon enough to be diſcontented. <hi>D'Olonne,</hi> who had beſtow'd much money in purchaſing her
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:42116:64"/> good favour, whether he regretted it, or was ſorry to be depriv'd of the pleaſure, accus'd the Marqueſs <hi>de Deffiat</hi> as the reaſon; and reported about, that he would be even with him; and to prove that he intended to be a man of his word, he hir'd ſome Bravo's to accompany him, and well arm'd, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed round the <hi>Hotel de la Ferté,</hi> ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if they found him there, he ſhould not return as he came. <hi>Deffiat,</hi> altho' the younger, ſhew'd himſelf the wiſer in this matter, telling thoſe who acquainted him with theſe extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that he would have nothing to do with an old Cuckold: That he ſeem'd to be angry, ſuſpecting he had robb'd him of his Miſtreſſes heart, but he had a better opinion of the Lady, than to imagin ſhe would continue a League with ſuch a ſort of a Man, when there were a thouſand more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving at her devotion.</p>
                  <p>I know not whether this diſcourſe was carryed to the Count <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> but his reſentment terminated in rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Mareſchalleſs: And meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her one day at a Lady's Houſe of her acquaintance, he reproach'd her with it, and told her ſhe had not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:42116:65"/> treated him with ſuch indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency. The Mareſchalleſs, willing that her Friend ſhould be deceiv'd in the fault imputed to her, with a great preſence of mind, anſwer'd, There is no great reaſon to wonder, Sir, I us'd you as my Brother-in-Law, whilſt you gave good uſage to my Siſter, but ſince ſhe has ſuch ill treatment from you, I know no obligation that claims a greater acknowledgment from my ſelf. Theſe words would bear an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that her diſreſpect proceeded from his ſeparation from his Wife, and was the firſt who ſpoke ill of her, and this was the explication the Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs hop'd the Lady would give 'em; but <hi>d'Olonne</hi> was too much concern'd to ſuffer it, and that the Lady might not be deceiv'd, No no, Madam, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> leave your Banters, they are too groſs to paſs upon the Lady. I ſpeak not of your Siſter, but your ſelf, to whom I have given ten thouſand Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols, in hopes you would be faithful to me, but I ſind I am not happier ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a Husband, or a Gallant, which I owe to my curſed Fate that drew me to addreſs my ſelf to your Family.</p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:42116:65"/>
                  <p>Theſe words, follow'd with ſome other reproaches, put the Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs into a great Confuſion, who think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Tears would perſwade her Friend of her innocence, having the command of them when ſhe pleas'd, ſo plentiful a Shower fell, that would have mov'd pity in any one who had not known ſhe had been ſo admirable a Comedian when ſhe pleas'd; in the mean time her friend, ſeeming to be perſwaded of the untruth, extreamly blam'd the Count <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> who on his ſide thinking her in earneſt, ſwore a thouſand Oaths to juſtifie the truth of what he affirm'd: She anſwer'd, ſhe could never believe it; but if it was ſo, the baſer Man was he to boaſt of things of that nature.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>d'Olonne</hi> had vented his anger, he withdrew, and the Mareſchalleſs ſwore after he was gone, that ſhe would acquaint her Husband with it; but ſhe never intended it. A ſevere fit of the Gout had long confin'd him to his Bed, and he was ignorant of the life ſhe had led for a time.</p>
                  <p>His indiſpoſition was the reaſon that he could not perceive the Intrigue between his Wife and the Duke of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:42116:66"/> 
                     <hi>Longueville,</hi> who was recovered, which would not otherwiſe have been diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult. For ſhe not only baniſh'd all Company for the Love of him, but denyed her ſelf to play, tho' it was her ſecond inclination. She fear'd leſt that affording a general liberty of coming to all who pleas'd, might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion his jealouſie. Their next inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view was at the <hi>Hotel de la Ferté,</hi> where the Duke giving her demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of a perfect health, he became ſo dear to her, that ſhe could have no quiet till they had paſs'd a whole night together; to oblige him to it, ſhe told him that her Husband being ill of the Gout, it was the ſame thing as if he was abroad, ſince he was incapable to ſtir, and the ſecurity being without ſuſpicion, he incurr'd no danger in it. The Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi>'s violent Flames, being a little appeas'd by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, he told her ſhe was in the right, but it was not reaſonable to run ſo great a riſque, when neceſſity did not compel it; that he agree'd with her, the Mareſchal could not ſtir out from his Bed, but yet ſeeing him come into the Houſe, it would be eaſie to obſerve he went not out again, which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42116:66"/> would ruin all their Affairs; that it was much better to meet abroad, and turn day into Night, where there would be no fears to interrupt their Joys, which ſeem'd to be what ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd. They were too well acquainted to continue reſerv'd, 'twas an Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as free as Nature ſhe deſired, and Careſs'd him till he agreed to yield her that contentment. He promis'd it ſhould ſpeedily be, and to keep his word, he deſired <hi>Fieſque</hi> to hire a Houſe in his name. He took one near St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi>'s Gate, where the Mareſchalleſs, pretending to go walk, ſometimes to the <hi>Arſenal,</hi> ſometimes to <hi>Vincenne,</hi> oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en came through a back Gate. The Petticoats began to riſe with theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terviews, and finding her ſelf with Child, ſhe was in ſome concern. Yet ſeeming to be careleſs of the reſentment of her Husband, to ſhew the greater violence of Paſſion for her Gallant, ſhe contriv'd ways to hide her great Belly, and was brought to Bed in her own Appartment.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> would not be there, but ſent <hi>de Fieſque</hi> in his place, who brought the Child away under a great Cloak. Whilſt he was
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42116:67"/> croſſing a Court to come to his Coach, the Boy cry'd, and fearing to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, he clapt his hand upon its mouth, and had like to have killed it. He carry'd it to the Duke, who was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting of it at a Houſe in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs St. <hi>Germain,</hi> where a Nurſe was provided. The delivery being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily over, ſhe wanted not an excuſe to keep her Bed, which made no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuſpect the Affair, not even the Mareſchal, who was ſwearing in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bed at every one that came near him, for he vented the vexation he had at his indiſpoſition, upon thoſe who had any buſineſs with him, tho' they were more deſerving than himſelf; for he had committed a thouſand Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Exactions, not to reckon the Eſtates of others that he had gain'd half by force, and half by addreſs.</p>
                  <p>It is not without reaſon that I ſay this, ſince it tends more to my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, than you may imagine, as you may judge by what follows. His Wife had ſome Lands near <hi>Orleans,</hi> and he, being deſirous to build, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large it, he bought a great deal of the Lands adjoyning, not valuing at what rate, ſince he did not deſign to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:42116:67"/> pay. One Gentleman amongſt the reſt, knowing how dangerous it is to have to do with a greater perſon than ones ſelf, had forbore as long as he could to part with ſome of his Lands, but being overpowered by force, he had parted with 'em twenty years with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out receiving one penny for principal or intereſt; at laſt by this means re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to great Wants, he threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the Kings feet, who ſtopt, and demanding of him the reaſon, he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a Petition, where his Caſe was ſtated in a few words. The King, who lov'd juſtice, ſent immediately to command the Mareſchal to give the Gentleman ſatisfaction, within eight days at fartheſt.</p>
                  <p>This Command was ſent him du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the lying in before mention'd, and you may imagine if his ill humour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded much quiet to thoſe about him. In fine, it happen'd that a Gentleman whom he had us'd ill, being an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Friend to the Count <hi>de Fieſque,</hi> was the next day after this Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, complaining of his treatment to him, and the Count anſwered him, that he was an old Cuckold, and he had no reaſon to think it ſtrange, ſince ſuch
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:42116:68"/> was his uſage to all the World, but his Wife was ſufficiently reveng'd of him, for not only her own but their quarrels to him. Whether we are delighted to hear ill of thoſe that have done us injuries, or whether out of a natural inclination to miſchief, he was ſo pleas'd at theſe words, that he deſir'd the Count, whom he found fully inſtructed, to tell him ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities; and he being ſo impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to content him, and at the ſame time to tell him that the Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs was now lying in, he departed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well ſatisfied. His deſign was not to let this ſtory be forgot, ſo he call'd for Pen and Ink, and his hand being not known to the Mareſchal, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated this advice to him, which he thought would not be very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably receiv'd.</p>
                  <p>This Letter came to the Mareſchal by the Poſt, for the Gentleman for that end had carry'd it himſelf to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtampes.</hi> The Mareſchal when he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd it, was very much ſurpris'd at the News, which he thought ſeem'd very probable, his Wife having for ſome time, pretended to be ſick, and the diſtemper neither increas'd nor
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:42116:68"/> diminiſh'd, and he was inform'd in Caſe he ſhould be incredulous, he might ſtill have an opportunity to clear his doubts. It is not eaſie to imagin what effect ſuch advice ſhould produce in ſo violent a Man: had the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchalleſs been in a condition to riſe, ſhe might eaſily have carried it off, but her good Fortune was, that his Gout confin'd him to his Bed, and he was incapable of any thing but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Reflections: So that, beſides the opinion that he was of, that the leaſt noiſe would be beſt for his Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he could not tell but he might be engaged for her upon the Gentleman's account, above mentioned, ſince it is not the cuſtom at <hi>Paris</hi> to lend Money to Ladies without ſomething under their hands, which would fall upon him.</p>
                  <p>Theſe two Circumſtances having not appeas'd his reſentment, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed thoſe ſeveral Conſequences he was meditating upon, he demanded not to be ſatisfied as he was counſel'd, knowing that after it he was oblig'd to keep no meaſures. Nevertheleſs he thought not the leſs, for the time of lying in being paſs'd, the Lady's di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:42116:69"/> vaniſh'd, and ſhe came into his Chamber in as good health as if ſhe had ailed nothing. As ſoon as he ſaw her, he began to cry out as if he had a fit of his Pain, and the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challeſs demanding the reaſon. Ah Madam, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> when you cry'd out louder than I do, not long ago, I did not ask you what was the matter, and therefore pray let me alone. Theſe words, which expreſs'd much without any poſitive meaning, gave the Lady occaſion to think; and that ſhe might not make any diſcoveries in her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, ſhe immediately retir'd; and the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> making her a viſit, ſhe told him what had happen'd to her, which did not at all hinder their accuſtom'd Entertainments. The Child's name was incerted in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which the Mareſchal receiv'd, ſo that he ſuſpected the Duke's Viſit, and after it he conſtantly, when a Coach came, enquir'd whoſe it was. He ſound every day the Duke was of the throng that viſited his Wife, and this aſſiduouſneſs confirm'd him in the truth of what he was inform'd of.</p>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:42116:69"/>
                  <p>The King at this time having War with <hi>Holland,</hi> every body of Quality accompany'd him, and the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> amongſt the reſt, then a Collonel of Horſe. The Mareſchalleſs parted with him leſs concern'd than might eaſily be imagin'd, it being oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by a little quarrel there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd betwixt them, upon the account of the Counteſs of <hi>Nogent</hi> whom he admir'd as ſhe had heard. There was but little likelihood of it; for this Counteſs, who was ſiſter to the Count <hi>de Lauſun,</hi> had neither his ſhape, air, nor Beauty; but it being difficult to cure a mind ſeis'd with Jealouſie, the doubt was ſo imprinted, that it paſs'd with her for a truth; and 'tis true, tho' all of it was not, yet a part of it at leaſt was certain, for undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Lady had a violent Paſſion for the young Prince, as ſhe manifeſted upon ſeveral occaſions.</p>
                  <p>However the King had fix'd the day of his departure, and the Duke took no great care to undeceive the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchalleſs, and he left her without clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the feuds between 'em; for he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be jealous of <hi>Bechameil,</hi> one of the dregs of the People, but richer
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:42116:70"/> then many of higher condition, which was a quality very Charming to her, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if it was accompanied with libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: But tho' the Citizen was very paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate, ſhe had made no returns to his Amour, for fear of angring the Duke, who had ſo declar'd againſt a ſharer, that ſhe durſt not ſhew the Complaiſance ſhe had for his Riches.</p>
                  <p>Having parted after this manner, few Letters paſs'd between 'em, which was to <hi>Bechameil</hi>'s advantage, for he found the means to make himſelf agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Mareſchalleſs, by offering at the ſame time to her Devotion, both his Purſe and his Heart. At firſt ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd both, apprehending leſt the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> might have left ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at <hi>Paris,</hi> to obſerve her Conduct; but this Prince having the ill fortune to be kill'd about ſix weeks after his departure, upon a Paſs on the River <hi>Rhine,</hi> ſhe was very ſorry ſhe had refus'd a Man that might be of advantage to her more than one way, after the loſs ſhe had receiv'd. All who knew this Princeſs's Intrigue, wonder'd ſhe ſhould receive ſo indifferently the news of his death, for ſhe was at the <hi>Thuilleries</hi> the next day, as merry as ever. It was not
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:42116:70"/> ſo with the Counteſs of <hi>Nogent,</hi> ſhe was ready to dye with Grief; but loſing her Husband on the ſame occaſion, it was a very good Colour for her extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary grief, and improv'd her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the Opinion of the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bechameil</hi> being rid of ſo dangerous a Rival, found a greater eaſineſs in his deſigns than he could have hoped for; for the Mareſchalleſs, dreading leſt he ſhould be quite diſcourag'd by her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal, writ him a very obliging Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to this purpoſe.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Mareſchalleſs <hi>de la Ferté,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Bechameil,</hi> Secretary to the Council.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THE World will have it that I have had a great loſs in the Duke of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueville, <hi>ſince he lov'd me paſſionately e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to merit a regret; it is a ſtrange thing they will pretend to judge better than my ſelf of what concerns me. It is true, my loſs has been very conſiderable, but they are ignorant of it, and if I may ſpeak freely, I know no other, but that of not having ſeen you for ſome time. I cannot gueſs the reaſon of it, unleſs it proceeds from my not granting all you deſir'd at firſt demand; but is it ſeemly to yield ſo ſoon?
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:42116:71"/> and becauſe I am of the Court, would you have me like thoſe Ladies, who are glad to begin an Intrigue by the concluſion? I am not of that faſhion, and tho' you ſhould never like me for it, I cannot repent me for not reſembling them.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bechameil</hi> was too underſtanding to miſs of the right interpretation of this Letter, ſo that arming himſelf with a Purſe charg'd with four hundred Piſtols, his time being dear to him, and unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to waſte it in fruitleſs words, with this good Succour, he march'd to the <hi>Hotel de la Ferté;</hi> where, To be ſhort Madam, <hi>ſays he,</hi> I heard that you loſt upon honour yeſterday four hundred Piſtols, and ſince perſons of Quality may ſometimes happen to be without ready Money, I have brought you that ſame to free you from the trouble of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing it elſe-where. The Mareſchalleſs underſtood his meaning but thinking it too low a rate to diſpoſe of her ſelf to a little Citizen. Sir, <hi>ſays ſhe,</hi> I cannot imagine who could tell you this, but he has only acquainted you with half my misfortune: I was ſo unlucky truly to loſe eight hundred, and if you could lend 'em me, I ſhould take
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:42116:71"/> it for a very great Obligation. Eight hundred Piſtols, Madam, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> that's a conſiderable Sum in this Age; but no matter, 'tis a Tryal I muſt make for your ſake; take nevertheleſs what I have brought, and I will give you my Note for the reſt, if you will not take my Word.</p>
                  <p>He ſaid this with ſo good a grace, that ſhe thought fit to truſt him till the next day, and telling him that all was at his Service, he began to return her thanks in kiſſing her hand. She after that offer'd him her face, where he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king too long a ſtay, What, Sir, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> dare you do no more till you have paid? let not that hinder you, your word, as I told you before, is ready money to me, and I wiſh withal my heart you were farther indebted to me.</p>
                  <p>She might ſay this perhaps for fear the man ſhould begin to conſider, and not taking his Merchandiſe, ſhould not think himſelf oblig'd to pay her; for ſhe could not be ſo covetous of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as out of deſire to enjoy it, thus to haſten the Concluſion. <hi>Bechameil,</hi> nevertheleſs, not at all ſurpris'd at the Diſcourſe (which would perhaps have
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:42116:72"/> ſtartled any other) Patience, Madam, <hi>crys he,</hi> every thing in due ſeaſon, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> was not built in a day. I am paſt five and fifty, and perſons of my age cannot ride poſt when they pleaſe. Theſe reaſons were too good and ſolid to be denyed, ſo that giving what time he required, he in fortus at laſt arriv'd where he deſir'd. The Lady, who would not have him depart diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, told him perſons of his age were to be admir'd, that there was nothing but Brutality in youth, deſiring him to afford her an hour or two of his Company as often as he could. The good man, who lov'd pleaſure when it did not endanger his health, imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhe demanded a meeting for the next day, excus'd himſelf upon ſome buſineſs he had at Council, but ſent her the remaining four hundred Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols, and ſhe thought it covenient to return him thanks for 'em in this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Letter.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Mareſchalleſs <hi>de la Ferté</hi> to <hi>Becha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meil.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ALtho' there is a great deal of pleaſure in ſeeing the</hi> Louis d'Ors <hi>you have
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42116:72"/> ſent me, yet let your opinion be what it will, they would have been more acceptable to me, had I receiv'd 'em from your own hands; but my greateſt diſſatisfaction is, that I muſt part with 'em, and that it is impoſſible for me to keep 'em, to ſhew you what eſteem I make of any thing that comes from you. The grief of it would kill me, did I not hope I ſhould not always be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, and that you on your part would often renew thoſe demonſtrations of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which will always be very dear to me. You would do me an injury to doubt of it, ſince one of your age muſt needs know how great an eſteem is always plac'd upon that which comes from a perſon belov'd.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>What! goodneſs! <hi>cry'd</hi> Bechameil, when he had read the Letter, has ſhe a mind to ruin me? and muſt I pay her ſo plentifully becauſe I am old? This Reflection, join'd with the little preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing occaſions of his temper, made the buſineſs at Council laſt three days long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than it would have otherwiſe done; but that being expir'd, he reſolv'd to go ſee if the money he had parted with, would be worth to him at leaſt another Viſit. The firſt word the Mareſchalleſs ſpoke to him, was, Ah Sir, I think I
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:42116:73"/> was born to be ever unfortunate, I loſt again yeſterday five hundred Piſtols. To her good fortune ſhe was ſo handſom that day, that tho' the Compliment did not pleaſe him, he return'd her this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Well, Madam, ſince it is ſo, don't deſpair, for you have ſome Friends left ſtill, who will not forſake you for ſo ſmall a matter. The Mareſchalleſs not at all doubting but his meaning was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to give 'em her down, or ſend 'em within an hour, gave him all the ſigns of acknowledgment ſhe could think of; but Company coming in, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of aſſuring the payment were broke, ſo that going before the others about ſome buſineſs, or rather with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated deſign, he forgot his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. There was a little malice in what he did, and he began to be weary of buying her good favour at ſo dear a rate; but that not anſwering her pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſhe writ him a new Billet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind him of his Promiſe. He ſent her the Money accompanied with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="141" facs="tcp:42116:73"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Bechameil</hi> to the Mareſchalleſs <hi>de la Ferté.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THE Leaſes of Farms are commonly made from nine years to nine years, and the Rent quarterly advanc'd. I ſpeak to you, as a Man of knowledge, ſince I am concern'd in 'em, and do not repent of it, becauſe it has taught me how to live. As I am then a man of Order, I muſt tell you it is impoſſible to continue a Commerce with you, when I know not how we are to agree. I will take a Leaſe of your Farm when you pleaſe, the rate and time of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be ſetled, but after that require no more of me; without this there will be no probability of ſubſiſting, and you will ſoon ſend me to the Goal.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>This Letter did not at all pleaſe the Mareſchalleſs, who expected the benefit of his Purſe as often as ſhe deſir'd; and as if the Merchandiſe had been worth his money, ſhe could hardly forbear returning him reproaches; yet ſhe ſtay'd ſome days to ſee if he would mollifie of himſelf, when fearing to loſe him, ſhe writ him theſe words.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="142" facs="tcp:42116:74"/>
                        <head>The Mareſchalleſs to <hi>Bechameil.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>I <hi>Am extreamly ſurpris'd at your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, ſince I have never ſaid or done any thing to diſoblige you. If we have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs with one another, there muſt be a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to regulate 'em, and you ſhall never find me againſt any thing that is reaſonable. But it is whole years ſince I have ſeen you, and this is the uſage is given from thoſe who pretend an occaſion to quarrel.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Pretend an occaſion, crys <hi>Bechameil,</hi> when he had red the Letter, and is four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand three hundred Livres in eight days time nothing, according to her reckoning; if this ſhould laſt, I muſt of neceſſity break, and it would be to little purpoſe to oppreſs the People, the Recompence would be but little, after ſo great a loſs. When he had ſaid a great many things to the ſame tune, he took his Cloak and Gloves, and went to her in great anger. The time that was requir'd to get thither had a little appeas'd him, ſo that when he arriv'd, Madam, ſays he, I come to ſee if we can agree about the price, I will tell you in a word the moſt I will give, if ten
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:42116:74"/> thouſand Crowns a year will do, 'tis at your ſervice, and pray let me know if you are contented. That's but a little for me, <hi>anſwered the</hi> Mareſchalleſs, I often play off as much in a day, and what muſt I do the reſt of the time? What, Madam, <hi>replyed Bechameil,</hi> cannot you live without Play? No, Sir, <hi>anſwered ſhe,</hi> 'tis impoſſible. She might have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo added, any more than without Love, but ſhe judg'd it properer to let him imagine it, than to mention it her ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bechameil,</hi> as much in Love as he was, had more concern for his Intereſt, ſo that being not pleas'd at the Anſwer, he threw up his head, which the Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perceiving, endeavour'd with all her Art to ſooth him. She ſaid then, that every body might live, he ſhould make it twenty thouſand Crowns; but he ſtorm'd at the propoſition, and ſwore he would not go one farthing beyond the ten thouſand he had offer'd, and waited only for her reſolution. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalleſs finding him ſo obſtinate, was oblig'd to be contented; yet ſhe would have a Bottle of Wine, becauſe, as ſhe ſaid, no bargains of conſequence were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made without it. <hi>Bechameil</hi> had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay againſt it, and the Bargain
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:42116:75"/> being concluded, he was oblig'd to pay her twelve thouſand five hundred Livres the next day. For ſhe would have a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before hand. Since he had acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd it in his Letter to be the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in thoſe Caſes. It was hard for him to part with the Sum intire, having not long before paid two ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ones; but conſidering ſhe could not after that demand any thing of him for three Months, he overcame his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, which was not the leaſt ſign he could give her of his Affections.</p>
                  <p>For theſe three Sums he enjoy'd the body of the Lady, for her heart was then in the poſſeſſion of the Count <hi>de Tallard,</hi> tho' he kept it not long, his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent being rather to pleaſe the Men than the Women. I cannot ſay who took his place, for ſhe had treated ſo many as if ſhe had lov'd 'em, that I might very well be miſtaken, ſhould I pretend to ſay who was her favourite.</p>
                  <p>The old Mareſchal ſtill kept his Bed with the Gout. He thank'd Heaven for ridding him of the Duke of <hi>Longueville,</hi> hoping according to the Italian Proverb, that ſays, <hi>The Beaſt being dead, the Venom dyes,</hi> the world would forget what was paſs'd; and one would have thought that
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:42116:75"/> he had forgot it himſelf, for when ſhe came into his Chamber, he call'd her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but my Love and my Heart, which were not the words he us'd to give her before. But to afford him a new morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, it was told him, that the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> had left a Baſtard, which the King intended to legitimate, he durſt not ask who was the Mother of it, but the Meſſenger of this news ſav'd him that Trouble, or rather threw him into a greater, by acquainting him that the Mother was conceal'd, and it might for that reaſon very probably be ſome mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed Woman.</p>
                  <p>The Mareſchalleſs, coming into his Chamber ſome time after, he no longer continu'd his ſweet words, but enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd her with Curſes, the common Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of his Diſcourſe. To be even with him, ſhe left him alone with his dogged humour, and went to comfort her ſelf with <hi>Bechameil</hi> who brought her a quarter of her penſion. 'Tis ſtrange this man who was as proud as common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe are who come from nothing, ſhould ſuffer her to play a thouſand tricks before his face; but the pleaſure to hear it ſaid, that he had the wife of a Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchal of <hi>France</hi> to his Miſtreſs, made him
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:42116:76"/> paſs over many things; and beſides ſhe had taken care to perſwade him that tho' there might be ſome appearances to the contrary, ſhe was nevertheleſs reſerv'd to him alone. But tho' he had often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly'd upon theſe excuſes, when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ſhe parted with what he gave her, to make her ſelf valu'd by others, it ſo incenſed him, that he writ her this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Bechameil</hi> to the Mareſchalleſs <hi>de la Ferté.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>I <hi>Break off the agreement I made with you, ſince you have fail'd to perform the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, You had oblig'd your ſelf to give the poſſeſſion of your heart to me alone, and now you would force me to partake it with an infinite number of others you rendezvous with every day. So that not being ſeis'd of the whole I am contented to part with what I had to the advantage of whom you pleaſe, or, to ſpeak properer, to the firſt Comer; in doing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I ſhall for the future employ my ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns in Manuring a ground which ſhall be till'd by me alone.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>The Lady was much troubled at this Letter, ſo conſiderable a Sum was of uſe to her, beſides the otehr preſents ſhe
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:42116:76"/> often wheedled from him. And truly ſhe had reaſon to be concern'd at it, for her husbands affairs went at this time ſo ill, that he who was once eſteem'd the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man in <hi>Paris,</hi> ſubſiſted wholly now upon the favour of the Court. For this reaſon ſhe did what ſhe could to recall him, but whether he knew there was no relying upon her word, which promis'd a better Conduct for the future, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he began to be tir'd with her, he would never hear any thing of it.</p>
                  <p>There being now not any of her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance Cully enough to furniſh for this Equipage, ſhe was oblig'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench her Expences, which was not a little trouble to her heart. Her Husband dying not long after, it grew worſe, and the Penſions ceaſing, ſhe was reduc'd to a lower ſtate. To better her Fortune, ſhe then reſolv'd not to play her ſelf, ſince ſhe had not wherewithal, but to afford an opportunity of playing at Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquenet at her Houſe, that the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage would accrue to her by it, might in a little meaſure comfort her for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary loſſes had happen'd to her in ſo ſhort a time. Every one being wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come for their Money, the ſharpers came thither, as well as people of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:42116:77"/> and one of the greateſt Note a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt'em, call'd <hi>du Pré,</hi> having inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated to her, that there were ſome ways to recompence her ill fortune in the World. Play was no ſecurer there than amongſt the other Cutthroat Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in <hi>Paris.</hi> This being diſcover'd by thoſe who were not of <hi>du Pré</hi>'s profeſſion, the Company leſſen'd, and the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by conſequence ceaſed, ſo that to make amends, ſhe drew a number of choice Women to her Houſe, in hopes that the report of their Beauty and Wit would invite the young people thither, and ſuch a meeting was eſtabliſh'd where all ſorts of tricks were practis'd to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford her a ſubſiſtence. Her chief deſigns were aim'd againſt the ſtrangers of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who having not yet heard of it, thought themſelves extreamly happy, to come and be ruin'd by her. One of her greateſt Confidents among the Ladies, was the Marchioneſs <hi>de Royan,</hi> and 'tis not to be imagin'd what they paſs'd upon every body. At laſt a <hi>Suiz</hi> Officer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt very much, and making ſome obſervations, made a a great noiſe of it as he had occaſion; but having to do with people of Quality, and being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd by his Friends to take heed of the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:42116:77"/> 
                     <hi>Baſtille,</hi> if he ſhould continue theſe ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, he took another courſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving printed papers which advis'd all ſtrangers that came to town to take heed of that Houſe, he fix'd it on all the gates of <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the Marchioneſs <hi>de Royan</hi> may be known to thoſe who have not had the happineſs to be acquainted with her, ſhe was the daughter of the late Duke of <hi>Noirmoutier,</hi> who having ſpent his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, leſt his Family in a condition to be pitied. This Lady then having no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to marry her, was forc'd to go into a Nunnery, very much againſt her incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, when the Count <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> who was of the ſame Family, fell in Love with her. He had for ſome time endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to make himſelf be belov'd by her, but being not agreeable enough to ſucceed in it, to make her the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate towards him, he thought of propoſing her a marriage with the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>de Royan</hi> his own Brother. There was nothing in nature more horrible than this Chevalier, both for his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Senſe: For tho' he was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crook'd nor maim'd, he had rather the air of a Cow than a Man, and was ſo plung'd in all ſorts of debauchery, that
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:42116:78"/> no people of Reputation would be ſeen in his Company. But how diſagreeable ſoever he might be, a Convent was yet more, in the opinion of this Lady, for ſhe not only reſolv'd to marry him, but alſo to pay her acknowledgments for it to the Count <hi>d'Olonne;</hi> 'twas by this means the Count arriv'd at his deſires, but before he would ſign ſome Writings whereby he ſetled his Eſtate upon his Brother in favour of this marriage, he would have her by all means grant him what ſhe had promis'd him, which ſhe faithfully perform'd like a Woman of Honour.</p>
                  <p>Thus it was, that the Count <hi>d'Olonne</hi> fearing there ſhould be no Cuckolds in the Family, took himſelf care of that Subject. In the mean time this Lady be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo well ſet out in the Paths of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, grew perfecter every day in all its methods, ſo that for Play and Gallantry ſhe was a ſecond to none, altho' ſhe had been educated under the Wing of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who had taught her other Leſſons. The Count <hi>d'Olonne</hi> who had a falling out with his Lady about this marriage, was reconcil'd to her and her Family, and this had occaſion'd that particular intimacy between the Marchioneſs <hi>de
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:42116:78"/> Royan</hi> and the Mareſchalleſs <hi>de la Ferte,</hi> who could not live without one another. <hi>du Pré,</hi> as I have ſaid before, finding 'em ſo well inclin'd, was their Maſter in teaching them to pack the Cards, and all the other ſlights in which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came very expert, but this Trade being not the beſt in the World, too many dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that ſort of Commerce, and every one growing ſuſpicious, the Mareſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs (no one being now left to forbid her the ſight of her Siſter,) took thoſe Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to rob her of <hi>Feruaques.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is impoſſible to mention the Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems ſhe us'd for that purpoſe, not out of covetouſneſs of his perſon which was not too engaging, but in hopes of ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his Fortune. For ſhe was vex'd at the very heart, that her Siſter, who was older than her ſelf by ſeveral years, and had not a better Reputation, ſhould have a purſe like his at her command, whilſt ſhe was in want of every thing. He had truly, either out of an exceſs of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or folly, made her ſeveral conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable preſents, and amongſt the reſt, a fine Houſe he had in <hi>Coqueron ſtreet.</hi> He was ſcarcely believ'd fool enough for this, tho' it was a general report about <hi>Paris;</hi> but the Counteſs, who was proud
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:42116:79"/> of the gift, which was nevertheleſs a ſign of the continuation of her ill life, would ſuffer 'em no longer to doubt of it, wherefore the Houſe being to be let, ſhe caus'd it to be incerted in the Bill, that they were to come to her to agree about the price.</p>
                  <p>Madam <hi>de Bonelle,</hi> who already lov'd her not much, being acquainted with this, ſent to pall down the Bill in the middle of the day, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs commanded another to be put up, and this was all the noiſe ſhe made at it. She was not ſo moderate with her Siſter, who, as I have already ſaid, would have rob'd her of <hi>Ferua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques,</hi> for they ſcolded ſo much at each other, that all the truth came out; this was not very commendable in two Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Quality, and eſpecially between two Siſters. Yet it was not very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, for the ſame accident hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to two others whom I could name, were it to my ſubject, however the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalleſs had it return'd to her, not long after from other hands, and the Duke <hi>de la Ferté</hi> her Son, who was the moſt debauch'd in the World; was of thoſe who took no great care of her Reputation. They had fal'n out about
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:42116:79"/> ſome concerns, ſo that he who had not Eſtate enough to furniſh her extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, could not ſuffer her demands of a Dower, and began by asking of her, if ſhe who had ruin'd his Father, had, notwithſtanding that, a deſign to rob him of al? The Mareſchalleſs, not mild enough to bear theſe reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, told him that he truly had great reaſon to complain, who was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſpis'd by the Court but the Town. This was nothing but the truth, but as all truths are not to be ſpoke; he could not bear it, but reply'd, if there was no reaſon on his ſide, there was yet leſs on hers, who was an old Wh—e, and hereupon he reckon'd up all that had to do with her, and the ſum amounted to threeſcore and twelve; a thing not to be credited, was not <hi>Paris</hi> ſufficiently ſatisfied of the truth of what I ſay.</p>
                  <p>The Mareſchalleſs bid him not forget his own Wife, who was as much to blame as any body; but the Duke ſtopt her mouth by telling her, he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well knew he was a Cuckold, but that did not hinder his Father from being one beforehand, in marriage, and after his death.</p>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:42116:80"/>
                  <p>Theſe reproaches had ſo diſcompos'd the Mareſchalleſs that ſhe began to cry, but ſhe had to deal with ſo tender hearted a man, that inſtead of being concern'd, he only laugh'd at her. The Comedy thus finiſh'd, ſhe made her Complaints to the Count <hi>d'Olonne,</hi> where he often went. You have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what you deſerve, <hi>anſwered the Count,</hi> and when your curioſity had led you from the Scepter to the Spade, how is it poſſible your affairs ſhould be leſs publick. Some former reſentments had occaſion'd this reproach, but when he had pleas'd himſelf with this, he promis'd her it ſhould not hinder him from correcting her Son; and meeting him about an hour after, he told him he was extreamly to blame in giving his Mother ſuch Language. That one of his years could not be ignorant, that nothing could excuſe the reſpect he ow'd her, and that if he did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him drunk when theſe words happen'd, he could not tell what to ſay to it. The Duke in all likelihood would be meditating ſome excuſes to colour ſo great a fault, or being very much aſham'd of it, would deny it; but without riſing or ſtirring, it is true,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:42116:80"/> 
                     <hi>ſays he,</hi> I was drunk, and 'twas very well for her I was ſo; I ſhould other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have told her ſome other truths, for I have ſo faithful a liſt of all her famous Exploits, that I know of ſo much as the Necklace of Pearl ſhe made the Chevalier <hi>de Lignerac</hi> cheat Mr. <hi>de Dreux</hi> the Counſellor of, there is nothing I am ignorant of. The Count ask'd him if he was not aſham'd to talk thus of his Mother, but all the Reprimands were too inſignificant to reduce him to reaſon.</p>
                  <p>As there were few actions paſs'd in the Kingdom unknown to the king, he was ſoon entertain'd with the diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Comedy, which made him have ſo ill thoughts of this Family, that he could not forbear diſcovering 'em. But the Duke <hi>de la Ferté,</hi> who knew his Reputation was already loſt with him, concern'd himſelf for it no more than the Mareſchalleſs, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd this way of living; ſo that perhaps I may ſome other time acquaint you of the reſt of her life, as well as the Story of Madam <hi>de Lionne,</hi> if they are ſtill ſo lucky to meet with thoſe who will accept of 'em, and Age as well as Shame does not bring 'em to Converſion.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
